Central Concert Park
中央演奏樂園
The Feast of Knowledge lecture begins
本知識饗宴演講會開始
We ask Vice President Peng Xuming to host for us
我們請彭旭明副院長為我們主持
Distinguished guests
各位嘉賓
thank you all for coming
謝謝大家來
Participate in the Central Actor hosted
參加中央演員主辦的
Feast of knowledge every month
每個月的知識饗宴
very honored today
今天很榮幸
Please go to the actor of the speedless department
請到無速系演員
to report
來報告
The interaction of this plant heritage with the environment
這個植物遺環境的互動
From seeing the sunrise
從看見日出說起
This physical strength is very attractive, right?
這體力就很吸引了對不對
that last month
那上個月
We invited Director Wu Junjie to speak about the typhoon
我們請了吳俊傑主任來講台風
After coming, it will be a typhoon night
來了以後就台風夜
Today is still typhoon night
今天還是台風夜
but also in the future
不過也是以後
I hope it won't be too windy and rainy
希望到時候不會風大雨大的
bother everyone
讓大家很困擾
but before we start
不過在開始之前
or let me briefly introduce
還是讓我簡單介紹
The experience of today's protagonist
今天的主角人的經歷
Dr. Wu grew up in
吳博士生長在
Although Kelian has
雖然客戀有
But I still want to introduce
但是我還是要介紹一下
Grows in the Ganan Plains
生長在加南平原
So 1985
所以1985年
Graduated from Chiayi Lingzhong
畢業於嘉義領中
Then 1989 and 1992
然後1989年跟1992年
Department of Botany, National Taiwan University
分別在台大的植物系
At that time it was called the plant department
那時候叫植物系
get a master's degree
得到碩士學士跟
Say yes, but now it's called the Department of Life Sciences
說是 但是現在已經改名叫做生命科學系
there are two masters
那有兩個主
The same he was at UC Davis in California
那一樣的他在加州那個 UC Davis
Later, I will share that I received a Ph.D. in 1997
待會是分享1997年拿到了博士學位
Then did postdoctoral work at the University of California and the University of Stanley
然後在加州大學以及史丹德大學做了博士後
Then the Academia Sinica came back in 2001 to start his academic career
然後2001年回來的這個中央研究院開始他的學術生涯
Once it can be called a job office at that time
那一旦能那時候叫職務所
Now it is also renamed as the Institute of Biological Sciences
現在也改名叫職務據維生物學研究所
that is now a researcher
那現在是研究員
The daily schedule is the basic basic scientific research of the job
那日過日程是職務的基本的基礎的科學研究
The main research topic is to get on this topic
研究課題主要就是登對這個題目
How does Deng feel about the environment in this position?
登對這個職務如何感受環境中的
this light message
這個光訊息
How messages are transmitted in cells and other related topics
細胞中的訊息怎麼傳遞等等相關的課題
Regulatory Mechanisms of Gene Expression
基因表現的調控機制
lots of research
很多的研究
The results are published in internationally renowned journals
成果都發表在國際有名的期刊
It has also won a number of affirmations from the domestic academic circles
也獲得多項的國內帶的學術界的肯定
Then he has rich enthusiasm to participate in basic scientific research
那他有富藏熱心參與基礎的科學研究
In addition to popular science knowledge delivered by the mass media
除了藉由大眾傳播媒體傳遞的科普的知識
Actively cultivate high school students and college students
有積極培育高中生跟大學生
Features in our Academia Sinica
在我們中研院的特色
It is also because he has continued to participate in promoting
也是他有繼續參與推動
Including international postgraduate students and more
包括國際研究生的學生等等
So is a very contacted researcher
所以是一個非常接觸的研究人員
let's applaud first
我們先讓大家鼓掌
Welcome to Wu Suxin
歡迎這個吳素新
Come give us this wonderful report
來給我們這個精彩的報告
Thank you Vice President for your introduction
謝謝副院長的介紹
Welcome everyone good night and very welcome today on a stormy night
歡迎各位大家晚安非常歡迎今天在風雨澆澆的夜晚
able to come here
能夠來到這裡
Give me the opportunity to be able to spend an hour and a half in the next hour or so
讓我有機會能夠在未來的一個小時一個半小時左右時間
Let me introduce the interaction between plants and the environment in my eyes
跟各位介紹一下我眼中的植物跟環境的互動
The interaction between plants and the environment covers a wide range of levels
那植物跟環境的互動所包含的層面非常的廣泛
So today I will explain to you the part I know better.
所以說我今天就我比較了解的部分來跟大家做說明
That is an interaction between plants and the light of the external environment
那就是植物跟外在環境的光的一個互動的情形
good
好
what's next
那接下來呢
Because this topic is set from seeing the sunrise
因為這個題目定的是從看見日出所起
So, I would like to introduce to you a little with a video about truth-telling photography.
所以說呢我想要先用一個說實攝影的影片跟大家稍微介紹
Will I block the audience here?
這邊的觀眾我會不會擋到
If you just wave and ask me to go away
你們如果就揮手請我走開
can be good
可以好
good
好
Well, to be honest, photography is basically to take a range of observation
那這個說實攝影呢就是基本上就是要把一個觀察的一個範圍
and then at different times depending on how long this happened
然後在不同的時間根據這個發生的時間的長短
after photography at different times
在不同的時間攝影之後
and play it in a fast way
然後以快速的方式來播放
This video is for you to see
這張影片給各位看的就是
After seeing a thousand flowers after sunrise
看見日出之後一個千流花
bloom after the sun
在朝陽之後綻放
time of day
在一天當中的時間
after noon
大概過了中午之後
this flower will wither
這朵花就會凋謝
we can watch it again
我們可以再看一遍
this is the flower
就是這個開的花
Then it was originally a darker purple in color
然後它的顏色本來是比較深的紫色
Then
然後
As the structure of this calico unfolds slowly,
隨著這個花布的構造慢慢地展開之後
it will fade slowly
它會顏色會慢慢的褪色
Then the life of this flower is only one day
然後這個花的生命只有一天
the next day if you say
隔天如果說
you guys have a chance to take a walk outside
各位有機會在外面散步
Look at the thousands of flowers on the roadside
看一下路邊的千流花
you can see a lot
大家可以看到很多
Different flowers bloom every day
每天都會開著不一樣的花朵
this is
這個是
Plants receive the message of light
植物接受到光的訊息
I know it's daytime
知道說現在是白天的來臨
Spread beautiful flowers throughout the day
在一天當中散發出漂亮的花朵
In addition to interacting with the environment
另外除了跟環境互動之外
Feel outside the light environment
感受到外在光環境之外
In fact, plants are also different from many
其實植物也跟很多不同的
Light the information inside to make some exchanges
光裡面的訊息來進行一些交換
For example in this
比如說在這個
In the crocus plant it is often
蕃紅花的植物裡面它常常在
It's naturally snowing inside
它自然裡面在下完雪
just in some colder places
就是在一些比較冷的地方
it this blade
它這個葉片
The part you see purple now is the part of the petal
你現在看到紫色的部分就是花瓣的部分
the part of the petal
那這個花瓣的部分
It has cells that are a little more medial
它有比較內側一點的細胞
There are also slightly outer cells
也有比較外側一點的細胞
the inner cell
那內側一點的細胞
When the temperature of light perception increases
感受光的溫度增高的時候
It grows faster
它的生長的速度會比較快
The outer side will grow a little slower
那外側會生長的稍微慢一點
so you can see
所以你就可以看到
let's watch it again
再我們再看一遍
you can see it in this
就可以看到它在這個
that side part
那側的部分
due to light
由於接受到光線
accept temperature changes
接受到溫度的變化
it grows faster
它生長的比較快
so it blooms
所以它就花朵就
beautiful open
美麗的打開
It is when the temperature rises during the day
就是在接受到白天溫度升高的時候
it feels some temperature changes
它感受到一些溫度的變化
Let out beautiful flowers again
再放出美麗的花朵
So I want to use these two
所以說我想利用這兩張
real photography videos
說實攝影的影片
Let everyone feel the beauty of plants
讓大家感受到植物之美
That's because when it comes to plants
那也因為講到植物
i think also
我想也
Those two videos just now were
剛才那兩張影片是
I from this Planche Emotion
我從這個Planche Emotion
Some videos of my job, I think maybe some teachers or students here might be interested
的職務的一些影片 我想可能在座可能有一些老師或是學生也許感興趣
You can also go to this website to participate, it is also a
那也可以到這個網站去參與 它也是一個
Full of hot teachers inside Indiana University
充滿了熱學的老師 在印第安娜大學裡面
It collects some animations and some videos of a lot of positions in motion
它收集了很多在運動中的職務的一些動畫一些影片
It can be used as a reference for everyone to observe the beautiful faces of various jobs
觀察各式各樣不同的職務的美麗的面貌可以供大家做參考
You can also go to this site to search
大家也可以到這個網站去做搜尋
Before introducing the interaction with the environment that we will talk about today
那在介紹今天要講的諸跟關環境的互動之前
I would like to welcome your time to introduce
我想歡迎您的時間跟大家介紹一下
My favorite research material and why
我鍾愛的研究材料以及為什麼
In all the research topics of so many life sciences
在這個所有這麼多生命科學的研究課題裡面
Why Study Botany
為什麼要研究植物學
Botany is like you can see that we are on the road every day
植物學就是像大家可以看到就是我們每天在路上
Or we can appreciate it in our surrounding environment
或者是在我們的周遭環境裡面可以欣賞
There is so much diversity and so beautiful
有非常多的多樣性 非常的美麗
Well, of course this is the evolutionary part.
那這個當然是演化的部分
It also includes fruits, vegetables, etc. that we often eat
在其中還包含我們常吃的果實 蔬菜等等
These are either seeds or antiquities these are plants
這些或是種子 或是古物 這些都是植物
the plant it also has
那植物它也具有
There is a lot of biological diversity
有非常多的生物的多樣性
For example, starting from Chlorella
比如說一開始從綠藻
Green algae slowly evolve in the water
綠藻慢慢在水裡面慢慢演化
After climbing onto land
到了爬到陸地上來之後
There are some dangerous plants
有一些臺險類的植物
some terrestrial plants
有一些陸生的植物
and then slowly evolved to the surrounding tube tree plants
然後再慢慢演化進展到圍管樹植物
get planted
進得到種植植物
There are flowering plants, snail plants, snail plants, etc.
有開花植物跟螺旨植物跟螺旨植物等等
So you can imagine that in this creature
所以說大家可以想像在這個生物
An evolutionary process in the plant kingdom
植物界的一個演進的過程裡面
It actually covers a lot
它事實上包羅了非常多
the environment it needs to adapt to
它需要去適應的環境
Climb from water to land
從水裡面爬到陸地
from dwarf ground plants
從比較矮小的地表的植物
Peritube trees
到開始長出圍管樹
and then until the planting starts
然後一直到開始產生種植
The use of planting has a relatively dry
使用種植有比較乾燥
can be stored to distribute
可以儲存的方式來散播
During these processes, plants continue to evolve
在這些過程裡面植物持續的演化
But in the process of evolution
但是演化的過程裡面
have been collecting some abilities
一直在收集一些能力
adapt the plant to
讓這個植物能夠適應
various environments
各式各樣不一樣的環境
in the process of evolution
隨著在演化的過程裡面
The natural world is constantly changing
自然界也不停地在變遷
The climate has also been changing
氣候也一直在變化
Plants must also be very full
植物也必須要很充滿
to adapt to changes in nature
要去適應大自然階的變化
After the plant has taken root and sprouted
因為植物生根發芽了之後
It must stay in this place to complete its life
它就必須要留在這個地方完成它的一生
So plants have to have a lot of different strategies
所以植物必須要有很多各式各樣不一樣的策略
To detect some subtle changes in the external environment
來偵測外在環境一些細微的變化
What to do with these changing plants
這些變化植物要怎麼辦
what am i going to do
我要做些什麼
and then be able to adjust themselves to the changes that best suit the environment
然後能夠調整自己到最適合環境的變化
This is a great feature of the plant
這個是植物的一個很大的特色
In addition, the survival of human beings, of course, also depends on the production of plants.
另外人類的生存當然也仰賴植物的產生
For example, a very simple plant in photosynthesis
比如說很簡單的植物在光合作用
Fish that fix carbon dioxide to make sugar
固定了二氧化碳製造糖類之魚
it also releases oxygen
它也釋放出氧氣
This oxygen is what we humans breathe
這個氧氣就供我們人類呼吸之用
So this is also the presence of plants that we have to rely on
所以說這也是我們要仰賴植物的存在
to be able to survive
才能夠生存
Plants are also primary producers
另外植物也是一級的生產者
see a special font
看到一個特別字號
making teacher's products
在做老師的產品
Feel sorry
抱歉
Plants are primary producers
植物是一級的生產者
I should have asked my daughter to help me change my size yesterday
我昨天應該讓我的女兒幫我改我的Size才對
So plants are primary producers
所以植物是一級生產者
It plays the role of converting the energy of light into chemical energy
它扮演了把光的能量轉化成化學能處理
present in sugar
存在糖類裡面
which can then be indirectly converted to
然後可以間接轉換成
some other human needs
其他人類所需要的一些
sources of energy, nutrients, etc.
能量的來源營養的物質等等
So plants are also the role of semi-wild primary producers
所以植物也是半野一級生產者的角色
In addition, plants contain many
另外植物還蘊含了非常多
Very rich in natural metabolites
非常豐富的天然的代謝物
some will talk about later
有些等一下會講到
maybe some
可能就是一些
Possible future source of new drugs
可能以後新藥的來源
or some antioxidants
或者是一些抗氧化劑
what we often eat now
我們現在常常在吃的
Some nutritional supplements, etc.
一些營養的補充品等等
So these are often derived from
所以說這些常常都是來自於
Some stimulating metabolites produced by plants
植物所生產的一些刺激的代謝物
or natural compounds
或是天然的化合物
That
那
even in Taiwan
即使在台灣就是
People's livelihood is rich
民生富裕
Then we often sometimes
然後我們常常有時候
can't feel
沒有辦法感受到
is what we need in life is in fact
是我們的生活所需事實上是
very sufficient
非常的充足
So we sometimes feel like saying
所以說我們有時候會覺得說
maybe some elite modified crops
也許一些精英改造的作物
We worry about it endangering our health
我們擔心它危害我們的健康
etc.
等等
But in fact this
但是事實上這個
Let me share with you my personal opinion
順便跟大家分享一點我個人的觀念
It is the existence of this elite modified crop
就是這個精英改造的作物的存在
sometimes it's not
有時候並不是
Maybe not
也許不是
and the life of this rich man
和這個富族的生活裡面
it may be an option to choose
它可能是一個可以選擇的選項
But for many other places in the world
但是對世界上很多其他的地方
source of some food
一些食物的來源
it may not be an option
它也許並不是一個選項
There are also a lot of malnourished children over there
在那邊還有非常多營養不良的兒童
It needs some high nutritional value crops
它需要一些高營養價值的作物
For example, these high nutritional value crops
比如說這些高營養價值的作物
For example, it can contain relatively high folic acid
比如說能夠含比較高的葉酸
or Vitamin A
或是維他命A
or some trace necessary
或是一些微量的必要
Metal elements such as new or iron, etc.
金屬元素比如說新或者是鐵等等
Then there are these nutrient-modified crops
那有這些營養改造過的作物
within these practical processes
能夠在這些實用的過程裡面
help these more remote areas
就幫助這些比較偏遠地區
Or children or adults in needy areas
或是有需要地區的小孩或者是成人
get enough nutrition
能夠獲得足夠的營養
can improve some
能夠改善一些
some of the life they face
他們所面臨的一些生活上
basic question
最基本的問題
Then maybe it's not something we need to think about every day
那這也許不是我們每天需要思考
or problems faced
或是面對的問題
But still many places in the world
但是還是世界上很多地方
Many people face daily
很多人每天需要面臨
A situation that needs to be resolved and needs to be combated
需要解決需要抗爭的一個狀況
even for us
那即使對我們來講
at present
目前
Maybe not, but the environment changes
也許不需要但是環境的變遷
Everything is actually changing at an accelerated pace
一切的變化事實上都在加快腳步
So for many botanists
所以對很多植物學家來講
Improvements that allow food crops to yield better
改進讓糧食作物能夠產量更好
Ability to resist the environment
能夠抵抗環境的利盡
Or some that can produce more high nutritional value
或是能夠更生產更多高營養價值的一些
Antiquities or products of some fruits and vegetables
古物或是一些蔬果蔬菜的產品
It's still a job that requires continuous effort.
還是一個必須要持續投注心力的一個工作
Because there's a chance it's not our problem today
因為這有可能今天不是我們的問題
Then the future may also be our problem
那未來也有可能是我們的問題
So in my mind
所以說在我的想法裡面
It's a constant work
這是一個需要持續努力的工作
So in the study of plants
所以說在植物的研究上面
There is also a large portion
也有很大的一個部分
It is betting on things like improving crops
是投注在類似在農作物的改良上面
Or find a way to give us a better
或者是想辦法讓我們有更好的
An effort on the source of the diet
飲食的來源的一個努力上
what's next
那接下來呢
These are just a few examples
這是剛才的這幾個例子
For example, we just talked about some
比如說我們剛剛有講到一些
Foods high in vitamin A, such as golden rice
含高維他命A的比如說黃金米
You can see us this is the white rice we usually eat
你可以看到我們這是我們平常吃的白米
That's rich in vitamin A
那這個是富含維他命A
so it looks a little golden
所以它看起來有點金黃色
That's why it's called golden rice
所以叫做黃金米
Then there is some water
那另外也有一些水
Other species have been modified
其他的品種有被改造過
So it has a higher iron content
所以它的含鐵量會比較高
For example, it is easier to absorb the environment
比如說它比較容易吸收環境裡面
Trace amounts of medium metals Necessary metallic iron
微量的中金屬 必需要的金屬鐵
So let encourage the iron content in it will be relatively high
所以讓鼓勵裡面的鐵含量會比較高
So let a lot of iron deficiency symptoms will produce some physical diseases
所以說讓很多缺鐵症狀會產生一些身體上的疾病
can also get some relief from using enigmas like this
也能夠因為使用這樣子的謎而得到一些紓緩
In addition, antioxidants are also a matter of great concern to everyone now.
另外抗氧化劑也是一個大家現在很關心的問題
That is to say, there are more free machines in the body
就是說身體裡面自由機比較多
May attack some macromolecules in cells
可能會攻擊細胞裡面的一些大分子
It will cause some damage or death of cells
會造成細胞的一些破壞或者是說一些死亡
At this time may add some
這時候就可能會補充一些
For example, like Q10 or like Huaqing tree, etc.
比如像Q10或者是像花青樹等等
some supplements that can also have antioxidants
這些能夠還有抗氧化劑的一些補充品
In fact, fruits and vegetables are a good natural source of antioxidant supplements
其實蔬果類就是一個很好的抗氧化劑補充品的天然來源
Here you see something that looks like an eggplant
在這裡你看到長得像茄子
it's not eggplant it's tomato
它不是茄子 它是番茄
It just has a relatively high amount of performance
它只是有表現比較高量
some pigments, these pigments are an antioxidant
一些色素,那這些色素是一個抗氧化劑
Because of the high amount of pigment produced
因為色素產生的量很高
So let this tomato grow a bit like a small round eggplant
所以說讓這個番茄長得有點像小型的圓的茄子
So it's a tomato full of antioxidants
所以說這是一個含糕抗氧化劑的一個番茄
Well those are just some examples
那這些都是只是一些例子
tell us again if some botanists
再來告訴我們是不是說一些植物學家
Or some researchers engaged in agricultural production
或者是從事農業生產的一些研究者
Some of the contributions he hopes to make
他所希望能夠做的一些貢獻
In this respect in the study of botany
在這方面在植物學的研究上面
able to contribute
能夠提供貢獻自己的力量
Then I think of course the obvious ones are the plants
那我想當然很明顯的就是植物
Not just a source of food
不僅僅是食物的來源
For example, we just talked about some
比如說我們剛剛講到了一些
Can provide some high nutritional sub-value crops
可以提供到一些高營亞價值的作物
crop products etc.
農作物產品等等
In addition, it also contains a lot of ingredients with new drugs developed
那另外呢他也含有很多帶開發的新藥的成分
For example, some anticancer drugs
比如說是一些抗癌的藥物
or some cancer drugs
或是一些化癌藥物
Or there are a lot of Chinese herbal medicines
或是從中草藥裡面有很多的
Separate many components
分離很多的成分
In fact, it is a source of opportunity for the development of new drugs
事實上都是一些開發新藥的一個契機的來源
In addition, plants are rich in cellulose
那另外呢植物裡面富含纖維素
of course it is
那當然是
Has long been used as a source for paper makers and paper products
長久以來已經是用作紙匠跟紙品的來源
In addition, what is now called renewable energy or reproductive energy
另外現在也所謂的再生能源或是生殖能源
From the plant kingdom can provide some
從植物界裡面可以提供一些
renewable is a can
renewable是一個可以
sustainable source of renewable energy
永續的一個再生能源的來源
These are some simple basics of some plants
這些是一些植物的一些簡單的基本上
The study of botany is not just about how plants grow and how they are planted
研究植物學不只是刀磡植物怎麼長怎麼栽種
How and when will it bloom?
怎麼什麼時候開花等等
even we'll talk about it later
就是我們等一下也會談到一點
In fact, there are more possibilities
事實上它還有蘊含更多的可能性
I hope there may be some high school students and college students or some parents here
希望在座可能有一些高中生大學生或是一些家長
In fact, consider
事實上也可以考慮一下
In the biological sciences, it may be considered to have a better understanding of botany
在生物科學裡面也許可以考慮多對植物學能夠有多一些的了解
Plants also have a very special
植物還有一個非常特殊
It is also impossible for animals to reach
也是動物沒有辦法達到
It's a very special feature
就是一個很特別的一個特點
That is to say it has a omnipotence
那就是說它有一個全能性
All omnipotence means
所有的全能性就是說
Usually it is difficult for us to cut off a hand
通常我們很難把一個手砍下來之後
Then grow a new innumerable
然後再長出一個新的無數性
A little difficult
有點困難
But for plants
但是對植物來講
Often most of the living cells in his body
常常他身體裡面大部分的活的細胞
can be removed separately
都可以單獨取下來
After being cultured, it becomes a cell mass
經過培養之後成為一個細胞團
After this cell mass has been cultured with a specific ratio of hormones
這個細胞團經過特殊的荷爾蒙的比例的培養之後
It is capable of developing into an independent spider
它是有能力可以發展成一個獨立的蜘蛛
So it means that inside the cell
所以就表示說細胞裡面
Most of the cells in the plant
植物體裡面大部分的細胞
Even though it has fully differentiated into
即使它已經完全分化成
sperm cells leaf cells flower cells root cells
精的細胞 葉的細胞 花的細胞 根的細胞
It still has that ability and that memory
它都還有那個能力 還有那個記憶
can be influenced by the environment
可以被環境的影響
Or an inducement of your external nutrient cultivation machine
或是你外在這個營養 培養機的一個誘導
able to bring the cell back to its original
能夠讓這個細胞重新找回它當初
as a clone
當作一個分身細胞
Or the so-called stem cells in animals
或是所謂的動物裡面常常講的幹細胞
such an ability
的這樣的一個能力
Able to turn itself back into a new spider
能夠讓自己再重新變成一個新的蜘蛛
Then this is I think this time in plant research is also a
那這個是我想這次在植物研究上也是一個
very unique
非常獨特的
a characteristic of plants
植物的一個特性
totipotency
就是所謂的植物的全能性
what's next
那接下來呢
Because the part I want to introduce to you today
因為今天要跟各位介紹的這個部分呢
The Arab world is often used as an example
常常會用到阿拉伯界來當作一個例子
So I also want to use this picture to introduce this to you
所以我也想用這張圖跟大家介紹這個
Thoughts that look unexpected on the side of the road
路邊看起來不期眼的想法
But in our hearts it's great
可是在我們的心中它是偉大的
A source of material for this study
這個研究的材料的一個來源
its name is arabian circles
它的名字叫做阿拉伯界
The Arab world may be related to its scientific name
阿拉伯界也許是跟它的學名有關
Is Rabidopsisifeliana
是Rabidopsisifeliana
It is a type of dicotyledonous plant
它是一個模式的雙子葉的植物
that's what it looks like
那就是它長的樣子
It's usually when we're on the side of the road
就是一般我們在路邊的時候
often seen
常可以看到
there may be no way to see
可能沒有辦法看到
exactly the same as this
跟這個完全一樣的
Because its original growth pair is not in Taiwan
因為它原本的生長對另不在台灣
but this is what it looks like in the lab
那但是這在實驗室裡面長的樣子
It has very cute little white flowers
它有非常可愛的白色的小花朵
four white petals
有四個白色的花瓣
with four two pieces
跟四個二片
Then there are six bear stamens and a magnetic stamen inside
然後裡面有六個熊蕊跟一個磁蕊
That's the structure of its calico
那這是它的花布的構造
So maybe you are not familiar with the Arab world
那這樣講阿拉伯界也許大家並不熟悉
But I want to talk about broccoli, white cauliflower, bok choy
但是我想講起青花菜 白花菜 小白菜
Vegetables that are common on these tables
這些餐桌上常見的蔬菜
Maybe everyone is familiar with it
也許大家就熟悉了
These vegetables are similar to the Arab world
這些蔬菜跟阿拉伯界
are cruciferous plants
都是屬於十字花科的植物
they are cousins
他們都是表兄弟姐妹
all in the same
都在同一顆裡面
They also have many similar characteristics
他們也有很多很類似的特徵
including the sequence of his genes
包括他的基因的序列
The way genes are arranged in the nucleus
基因在細胞核裡面排列的方式
has its very similar place
都有它非常類似的地方
So the Arab world like this
所以以這樣子的阿拉伯界
to be used as research material
來當作一個研究的材料
In fact, it can be used as a good springboard
事實上可以當作一個很好的跳板
For these varieties of some of our common vegetables
對這些我們常見的一些蔬菜的品種
and its application
以及它的應用
or possible future modifications
或是未來可能的改造
can have a good foundation
都可以有一個很好的基礎
Use this Arab world for research
利用這個阿拉伯界來做研究
it has many benefits
它有非常多的好處
For example, it grows for a short time
比如說它生長的時間很短
It takes about two or three months to complete a life cycle
大概兩三個月就可以完成一個生命的週期
its spider is small
它的蜘蛛很小
More suitable for cultivation in the laboratory
比較適合實驗室裡面栽培
It also produces a lot of seeds
它也會產生很多的種子
It is more convenient to do some genetics in the laboratory
比較方便在實驗室裡面做一些遺傳學
Write cell blood in other aspects
其他方面寫細胞血啦
or biochemistry
或是生物化學
Research related to molecular biology
分子生物學相關的研究
That's an Arabian sword
那這個是阿拉伯劍
can see him
可以看到他
In my eyes are lovely little white flowers
在我的眼中是可愛的小白花
And then it's his
然後呢這是他的
Looking down from the top there is a
從頂上往下看有一個
structure resembling whorled leaves
類似輪生的葉子的構造
this is arabic sword
這是阿拉伯劍
That's because wait a minute
那也因為等一下各位會
may see some videos
可能會看到一些影片
pertaining to individual plants
是有關於植物的個體
That is, what does a plant seedling look like
就是說植物幼苗長什麼樣子
I believe that everyone may be like me
我相信大家可能跟我一樣
will start from elementary school
在從國小就會開始
Put toilet paper in a small box
在一個小的盒子裡面鋪衛生紙
Then the teacher will ask us to go home and plant mung beans
然後老師就會叫我們回家種綠豆
or red beans
還是種紅豆
that's all that
那都是那個
I used to be taught by my mother to water
以前我是我媽媽教的水
Then my retribution is
那我的報應就是
My daughter's water is what I taught
我的女兒的水是我教的
So I think everyone has gone through this
所以我想大家都有經過這一段
that's why i didn't understand
那所以就沒有理解
Then I don't know everyone at that time
那我不知道大家那個時候
Besides teaching water or looking at this seed
除了教水或是看這個種子
This process of germination is observed
發芽的這個過程進行觀察
Then teach the teacher's homework
然後教老師的作業之外
Have you ever looked at it carefully?
是不是也曾經仔細的看過
what do these plants look like
這些植物到底長什麼樣子
what does it look like
什麼樣子
So let's briefly review today
所以我們今天先來簡單複習一下
what does this plant look like
這個植物長什麼樣子
Then because of this wait will follow
然後因為這個等一下會跟
some videos you'll see
會看到的一些影片
It has something to do with the shape of the plant
它植物長的樣子有點關係
So let's take a moment to look at
所以我們先花一點時間看一下
Then in the meantime I'll do a little bit of a comparison
那在同時我也會稍微比較一下
What are the differences between animals and plants
動物跟植物有些什麼樣子的差異
And then I think you've sort of figured out
然後我想各位已經有點發現
my speech is very fast
我那個講話很快
then i usually talk about
那我通常講到
I think when I say happy things
我覺得說很開心的事情的時候
will speak a little faster
就會講得再更快一點點
So please don't remind me of this
所以這個大家就不要客氣提醒我
slow down or say
放慢速度或者是說
I just feel like saying it again when I need it
在有需要的時候就是又覺得說
I didn't know you told me about the process of measuring
我量的過程是不知道你跟我講
Just raise your hand a little bit to remind me
就是說稍微舉個手提醒我一聲
then we can
然後我們可以
To explain is to discuss
講解就是討論一下
then we can go on
然後我們可以再繼續
then this is
那這個是
Embryo development in the Arabian kingdom of Mosz
摩斯茲阿拉伯界胚胎的發育
with it there will be in the end
跟它最後會有的
a form of seedling
幼苗的一個形態
That plant is embryonic development
那植物這個是胚胎發育
Furthermore, the development of direct motion is the same as that of plants
再就是說發育直動跟植物一樣
After the sperm and egg unite
就是精子跟卵子結合了之後
an embryo is formed
就形成了一個胚胎
inside the embryo
那這個胚胎裡面
The embryo of the plant is planted inside
植物的胚胎就是在種植裡面
But in the plant it will start to do the initial development
但是在種植裡面它就會開始做初步的發育
What did you develop into?
發育到什麼呢?
developed to resemble a natural lesion
發育到有點像自然病痕
slightly bigger than this
比這個稍微大一點
The process starts here
這個過程從這裡開始
That is, there is a tail blowing under it
就是它下面有吹著一個尾巴
This will naturally degenerate
這個自然會退化掉
There is a spherical structure on it
上面有一個像球狀的構造
will start
就會開始進行
like cutting a watermelon
就像切西瓜這樣
Cut a knife and split from this side
切一刀從這邊分裂
Divide once more to double the number of cells
再分裂一次就變成兩倍的細胞
or cut once from this side
或是從這邊切一次
Divide that way and double the number of cells again
再往那邊分裂就會再變成兩倍的細胞
so you'll see it
所以你就會看到它
Like cutting and scraping, after re-cutting
像切一刮要橫切重切之後
You slowly start to grow more and more cells
你慢慢就會開始長得越來越多的細胞
Those cells are slowly growing up
那些細胞慢慢在長大的過程裡面
will start to divide into different parts
就會開始分不同的部位
Different parts will do different things in the future
不同的部位以後會做不一樣的事情
For example, here is the color
比如說這裡有顏色
The green part will grow longer in the future
綠色的部分以後就會長成比較長
The structure here
這裡的構造
Seeing this here, everyone may start to be a little familiar
這裡看到這裡大家可能開始有點熟悉
Because I saw a little belly seedling
因為看到有點小肚苗的樣子
Then these are the two cotyledons of Xiaodu seedlings
那這就是小肚苗的兩顆子葉
It's the first pair of leaves to grow
就是第一對長出來的葉子
These two pairs of cotyledons
就是這兩對子葉
Then this part may become the essence of plants in the future.
那這個部分也許會變成以後植物的精
For example, Xianpixian is immediately the trunk of a tree
比如說鮮皮顯立即是樹的樹桿
That's where the bean sprouts eat that body part
那就是這個豆苗吃那個身體的部分
Then the bottom part is where the roots will grow later.
那下面這個部分就是以後會長出根的地方
So it's basically a small plant
所以說這是一個基本上就是一個小的植物的
Miniature Leaf Seedling Embryo Seed
葉苗的縮影在胚胎裡面 在種子裡面
it looks like this
它就長這樣
What about after it grows up, after it sprouts, after its roots protrude?
那這個長大之後 發芽之後 根突出來之後呢
The gold cloth will also lengthen and the plant leaves will start to tilt up
這個金布也會延長 然後植葉會開始往上傾
will then open
然後會打開
So basically, the shape of the leaf seedling is the root
所以說基本上就是 葉苗的形態就是根
then gold cloth then leaves
然後金布 然後葉子
There is another very interesting place in the middle
那中間還有一個很有趣的地方就是
the place painted red
畫紅色的那個地方
this place
這個地方
this place is plant
這個地方就是植物的
Plants are very different from animals that is to say
植物的動物很不一樣的就是說
In the embryo it grows like this
在胚胎裡面它就長到這樣
It stops and waits for germination before doing the next thing
它就停了 然後等待發芽之後再做下一步的事情
But people are different, right?
那可是人就不一樣對不對
People grow up before they are born
人在出生之前就長好了嘛
It's a face with a tile face, and the horns of the hair have grown back
是肢瓦臉 頭髮角 長好了
But without plants, plants grow like this
可是植物沒有 植物就長這樣
So let's say we're talking about a lotus flower
所以說我們在比如說一個荷花
We did not see a single lotus in the seeds
的種子裡面 我們沒有看到一顆小荷花
Then
然後
All of them have grown into the same shape
都已經長好各部形態的一個樣子
it grows here
它就長到這裡
it's stopped
它的停止
Then the wait is to say
然後等待的就是說
this growing point
這個生長點
so-called avatars
所謂的分身組織
or growth point
或是生長點的部位
the growth point
這生長點的部位
the location of the so-called stem cells
就是所謂幹細胞的位置
but stem cells
但是幹細胞
Are you looking for me?
你這找我的嗎
What about the stem cells?
這個幹細胞呢
is after
就是之後
stimulated by the environment
受到環境的刺激
after it grows
它長出來之後
It's going to do all the other roots
它要做所有其他的根精業
new karma
新的業子
will bloom later
以後要開花
when there will be results
會要結果時
or to produce seeds
或是要產生種子
from these stem cells
都從這些幹細胞來
so it was not decided at that time
所以它那時候還沒有決定
The seed has not been decided yet
那種子的時候還沒有決定好
Then the environment tells it
之後環境再告訴它
when will it grow
它什麼時候要長
what will it look like
要長成什麼樣子
much longer
要長多多
So this is also related to animals
所以這也是跟動物
very different place
非常不一樣的地方
then we know now
那我們現在知道了
this basic form
這個基本的形態
we can see the next one
我們可以來看一下下一張
What about the next one?
那下一張呢
we're going to take a look
我們就要來看一下
i remember seedlings
我記得幼苗
The way it grows under the light
它在光照下面生長的樣子
So what we see now is
所以我們現在看到的是
a local
一本土
Then a small seedling will emerge from inside
然後裡面會發出一顆小幼苗
What about that little seedling?
那那個小幼苗呢
I just introduced to you
就有剛才我跟各位介紹
This paper leaf and this extension of this gold cloth
這個紙葉還有這個金布的這個延長
we can take a look
我們可以來看一下
What you can see here is
在這個你可以看到的就是
So here's a cute little seedling highlighting the chart
那這裡有一顆可愛的小幼苗突出這個圖表
Then these two are paper leaves
然後這兩個就是紙葉
This is the gold cloth, the gold cloth is extending
這是金布,金布在延長
Then Paper Leaf went to look for it in the animation
然後紙葉在動畫中去開始找找看
where is the light where is the light
光在哪裡,光在哪裡
when i want i want this paper leaf
我要什麼時候我要把這個紙葉
Where can I hold it?
撐到哪裡撐多大
in what direction wait
向什麼方向等等
that in this process
那在這個過程裡面
everyone can see it
大家可以看到它
A piece of paper is also slowly, and the leaves of the paper are gradually getting bigger
一紙也慢慢,紙葉也慢慢在變大
Then it slowly turns green
然後也開始慢慢變綠
So after the light shines at this time
所以說在這個時間照到光之後
Start the process of turning green
開始變綠的這個過程
It means that the chloroplasts in the cells start to develop
就表示細胞裡面的葉綠體開始發育
After the chloroplast develops, there are
那葉綠體發育之後有
after chloroplast
葉綠體之後
it can photosynthesize
它就可以進行光合作用
carry out photosynthesis
進行光合作用
it can start making starches, sugars
它就可以開始製造澱粉,糖類
began to perform his role as a primary producer
開始執行他當作一級生產者的一個角色
So that is
所以說那個是
I think the condition of the seedlings to germinate under the light
我覺得幼苗在光照下面發芽的狀況
What about the seedlings?
那幼苗呢
Then you can see this little paper leaf just now
那剛才你們可以看到這個小的紙葉呢
watch the light go round and round
看著光轉來轉
I also find this interesting
那這個我也覺得很有趣
This is a sunflower seedling
這個就是一個向日葵的幼苗
And what about these poor sunflower seedlings?
那這些可憐的向日葵的幼苗呢
Why is he so like that five-year-old boy
他為什麼這麼像那個五歲的小男生
just grinning
就是咧咧咧咬這樣
just keep moving
就是一直動來動去
Is it because of these poor sunflower seedlings
是因為呢這些可憐的向日葵的幼苗
grow in a low light situation
生長在一個低光照的情況之下
because of low light
他因為低光照
So I don't know if everyone will be like me
所以我不知道大家會不會跟我一樣
I have some experience
有一些經驗就是我啦
Even though I study plants
就是我雖然研究植物
so the only thing i can grow is my plant
所以我唯一能夠種的我的植物
It is the material of my experiment
就是我實驗的材料
So I will often put my plants in the comparison
那所以我會常常把我的植物放在比較
dark place
陰暗的地方
So the plant will grow
所以說這個植物就會土長
Therefore, the soil grows rapidly in terms of his progress
所以土長就他的進步長得很快
That native has a big shortcoming
那土長有一個很大的缺點
It's just that he won't be able to support him at first
就是他開始會支撐不住他的
When the leaves grow, he will fall down
長出來了葉子他就會倒伏
That said, at home you have some plants that look
那就是說在家裡各位有一些植物看起來
looks different from fancy
長得跟花式不大一樣
why is fancy so small yours is so big
花式為什麼這麼小你的這麼大
then please give him more sunshine
那請給他多一點陽光
So these plants
所以說這些植物
because it is placed under relatively low light conditions
被因為放在比較低光照的情況之下
So he poked his head around and kept looking
所以他頭在探來探去一直在找尋
where is there more sun
到底哪裡有多一點太陽
how much sunshine can go
到底有多一點陽光可以去
Except he was in the process of searching
他除了在找的過程裡面
You can also see that he has been growing this golden cloth structure
大家也可以看到他一直在長這個金布的構造
This is the long-term process I just talked about
這是我剛剛講的一個土長的過程
His golden cloth is excessively extended
他的金布過度的延長
so
所以說
The search for the head is that the head is too heavy
頭的尋當就是頭太重了
so there is no way to compound
所以就沒有辦法復合
he'll start falling
他就會開始倒下來
Overwhelmed
動倒西外
So this is also a
所以這也是一個
An example where light is important for plants
光照都植物很重要的一個例子
Why
為什麼
he needs to find him
他需要找他
That
那
The next thing we will talk about is
接下來我們會講到的就是
Except we were just in low light
除了我們剛剛在低光照
Then see the process of seed germination
然後看到種子萌養的過程
Then I want to give a simple example
那我想舉一個最簡單的例子
just to let everyone understand
就是讓大家明白
light on plant growth
光線對植物的生長
where is its importance
它的重要性在哪裡
Then the simplest comparison is
那這個最簡單的比較就是
germinate the seeds in the dark
把種子放在黑暗裡面發芽
Germinate in the light
跟放在光照裡面發芽
then look at
然後看看
Let's see what's the difference in their appearance
我們來看看他們的外表性的差別是什麼
then let's go first
那我們先來
After a little concept
有一點概念之後呢
let's talk a little more
我們再講稍微多一點
Then how to use this
然後怎麼利用這個
Then this is the right seedling of sunflower sprouting in the dark
那這個是向日葵的右苗在黑暗裡面發芽
Germinate in the light
跟在光照裡面發芽
If you germinate in the dark, it depends on how big its head is.
在黑暗裡面發芽你就看它的頭不大也要百分之
It's just in the dark it won't be affected
它就是在黑暗裡面它不會受到什麼影響
The crystal cloth is continuously extended
晶布就不斷的延長
On the other hand, in
那反觀在
The right seedling of this sunflower grew under the light
光照下面生長了這個向日葵的右苗
you can see it
你就可以看到它
Here its leaves begin to open
在這裡它的葉片開始打開
The extension of its lower shaft does not
它的下佩軸的延長沒有
That is, the extension of the crystal cloth is not so obvious
就是晶布的延長沒有那麼明顯
Then this part you can see it this
那這個部分你可以看到它這個
Part of the crystal cloth of the leaves is not opened at all
植葉的部分晶布完全不打開
right
對不對
It's where the two leaves wrap together
它就是這個兩個植葉包在一起的地方
it just has a tick
它就是有一個勾勾
Next time you go to the vegetable market to see bean pepper dishes
下次大家到菜市場去看豆椒菜的時候
I'll see more in just a few moments
只有一許就會多看一下
it will have a tick in there
它就會有一個勾勾勾在那裡
Hook it there so the two leaves are also put together
勾在那裡它兩個植葉也合在一起
And what remains together is a very
而殘留在一起這是一個很
It is an important protection measure for plants
對植物來講是一個很重要的保護措施
that is
就是
Remember what I just said about the stem cells that grow the electric plants?
記不記得我剛剛講的生長電植物的幹細胞
to grow all the leaves
以後要長出所有的葉子
the place that gave me ten seeds
給我十種子的那個地方
That place is wrapped in the middle of the two leaves
那個地方就包在兩片植葉的中間
so you can think
所以你可以想
I imagine a plant moulting in the dark
我想想看一個植物在黑暗裡面蒙牙的時候
When it wants to break through the limit of the soil, when it is about to rise
它要衝破這個土壤這個限制的時候要往上漲的時候
It will definitely not want to keep rubbing it so important with the cells and the soil
它一定不會想要把它那麼重要的跟細胞一直跟土壤摩擦
and then maybe some damage, right?
然後可能造成一些損壞對不對
So the ideal way is to wrap it in the leaves
所以說很理想的方式就是把它包在植葉裡面
Then use this curved cell to withstand
然後利用這個彎曲的這個細胞頂住
Gold cells withstand
金的細胞頂住
jack it up until after it sees the graph
把它頂頂頂到它看到圖表之後
It floats when it sees the sun
看到陽光之後它才會浮陣
Then the two leaves will open
然後兩個植葉才會打開
This is what we just saw on the right
這是剛才我們在右邊看到的
This section you can see it this
這個部分你可以看到它這個
this crooked place opens up
這個彎曲的地方打開了
The leaves are opened
植葉已經打開了
Then this time is a place to grow
那這時候是個生長點的地方
In fact, in the middle of the two leaves
事實上是在這兩片植葉的中間
At this time it receives the light message
這時候它接受光訊息
It knows that my environment is right now
它知道我現在環境對了
I can start doing what I'm going to do with my life
我可以開始做以後我這一生要做的事情
then we saw
那我們看到了
right side of arabian border
阿拉伯界的右面
Right side of assortment of different plants
各式各樣不同植物的右面
in the light
在光照跟
What grows in the dark
黑暗裡面生長的情況
when growing in darkness
那在黑暗裡面生長的時候
It's just a very long groove with this lower shaft
它就是有非常長的這個下佩軸的溝槽
then there are two
然後有兩個
There is this curved hook
有這個彎曲的這個hook
The so-called ticked places
所謂的一個一個勾勾的地方
Then there are two sides practicing
然後有兩邊執業
small and yellow
也很小也很黃
The karmic body has not yet begun to develop
業力體也沒有開始發育
Has not yet started photosynthesis
還沒有開始進行光合作用
What about the plants that grow under the light?
那在光照下面生長的植物呢
On the other hand, it will make relatively short progress
就反過來講它就會比較短的進步
Then there is the open practice
然後有打開的執業
Then the growth point in the middle also starts
然後這中間這個生長點的地方也開始
Know I'm in the right place to start
知道我在對的地方可以開始做
Things that will grow leaves in the future
以後長葉子的事情
So basically speaking, there are probably two important points
所以說基本上來講呢大概有兩個很重要的地方
One is that the extension speed of the so-called lower shaft will slow down under the light
一個就是所謂下佩軸延長的速度會趨緩在光照下面
So it doesn't have to be extended that much
所以它不用延長的那麼多了
It's enough to extend that much
延長那麼多就足
what we just said is harmless
我們剛剛講的足無百害
what about the other
那另外呢
that is
就是
This career also develops karmic experience and begins to develop
這個職業也會開展業力體會開始發育
Then this top avatar organization also began to have the ability
然後這個頂端分身組織也開始有能力
make new leaves
製作新的葉子
Then this is the most basic
那這個是最基本的
It is the difference in the development of plants under light and non-light
就是光照跟非光照下面植物的一個發育的一個不相同
Although we said later, wait a minute, we will
那雖然說我們之後呢等一下我們會
study with many concepts like this
用很多這樣子的概念來研究
that biologists would want to know
就是生物學家會想要知道說
Well, how do my plants know that the light is coming
好了那我植物怎麼知道光線來
How do I know I'm sticking out
我怎麼知道我突出突表了
how do i know when i'm going to do these things
我怎麼知道我什麼時候要做這些事情
So according to this observation of nature
所以說根據這個對自然界的觀察
Knowing the difference between the two forms
知道這兩個形態上的不同之後
This can be used as a basis
這就可以當作一個基礎
Let the botanists study
來讓植物學家去研究
Ok, let me compare the differences between the two.
好那我來比較看這兩種的差異
where and how the difference arises
差異在哪裡是怎麼產生的
What if I don't look so good
那萬一我沒有長得這麼好
I look a little white
我長得有點白白的
I look a bit my career is not open
我長得有點我職業不打開
what the hell happened
那到底是發生了什麼問題
Then by exploring the question
那藉由去發掘這個問題
to understand how plants feel
就能夠了解植物到底是怎麼樣感受到
A change in ambient light
外界光的一個變化
good
好
The change of external light is also very complicated.
那外界光的變化也很複雜
This is a
這是一個
A spectrum from ultraviolet to visible light
從紫外線到可見光的一個光譜
The ultraviolet light is about 300 nm or below
那紫外線大概是在300個nm或以下
In fact, visible light is about 400 to 800
那其實可見光大概是400到800左右
From which, red, orange, yellow, green, and blue electrons can be separated
那從其中可以分紅橙黃綠藍電子
Then what
然後呢
That is, blue light has a shorter wavelength
就是藍光在波長比較短的地方
then green, then red, then red
然後再來是綠色,再是紅色,再來是紅光
So it naturally has so many shades of different colors
所以它自然裡面有這麼多不一樣的顏色的色光
And the morning is different from the afternoon
而且早上跟下午還不一樣
when you are at noon and when you are in the evening
你中午的時候跟你傍晚的時候
The ratio of the light is not the same
那光線的比例還不相同
So how do plants know what time it is?
所以說植物怎麼知道我現在是幾點了
so how do i know it's morning
所以我怎麼知道是早上
Then it's evening
然後還是說是傍晚
what time is my light
那我什麼時間的光線是什麼
what am i going to do
我要做什麼事
So what about plants
所以說呢,植物呢
after receiving the light
接受了光線之後
it can do many things
它可以做很多的事情
Let me tell you what plants can do
那先跟各位介紹一下植物能夠做什麼事情
Then I'll introduce you later
那等一下再來跟各位介紹
Why do plants do these things
植物為什麼可以做這些事
Here, light affects the life of the plant
在這裡呢,光影響了植物的一生
In fact, I have been doing light since I was studying for a Ph.D.
其實我從念博士班開始就是做光
The bad light in biological research has also affected my life
生物學研究搞不好光也影響了我的一生
So where does this light-affecting plant doctor begin?
那這個光影響植物醫生從哪裡開始呢
Start with the middle bud
從中置萌芽開始
So its pretty low level in the chart
所以說蠻在圖表裡面太底層的
He receives little light to stimulate his germinated seeds
他接受到不到微弱光線刺激他發芽的種子
often useful
常常也會有用
Some troubles above germination
發芽上面的一些困擾
Light guides plant germination
光線右導植物的萌芽
We've just seen a lot of lighted and unlit times
我們剛剛看了很多照光跟不照光的時候
the difference in its external form
它的外部形態的差異
just this crooked one
剛剛這個彎彎的這個
GoGo
GoGo
when it's in the soil
就是在土壤裡面的時候
Protect this apex clone
保護這個頂端的分身組織
After shining the light, there are two open words
照了光之後就有兩個打開的字眼
This so-called de-whitening phenomenon
這個所謂的去白化的一個現象
In addition, in the natural world, it is like a white race, right?
另外在自然界裡面是像狀況白白種對不對
Sometimes you'll see plants growing under shade
有時候你會看到植物生長在遮陰下
it's my plant
就是我這個植物
Two older brothers and a younger brother grow up in the middle
兩個大哥跟一個小弟長在中間
This little brother said yes
這個小弟就說好啊
I can't get enough sunlight
我接受不到足夠陽光
It's very bad for my growth, isn't it?
非常不利於我的生長對不對
but it doesn't matter
可是沒關係
it can feel
它可以感受到
it is now at a disadvantage
它現在處於劣勢
Not because its siblings are all big
並不是因為它的兄弟都長得很大
it feels oppressive
它感受到壓迫感
Rather, it feels the tension between the two big brothers
而是它感受到在這個兩個大哥中間的
The light environment is different
光的環境不大一樣
The quality of light varies
光的品質不大相同
Its light is far more yellow
它這個光遠黃光比較多
So this little plant feels far yellow
所以這顆小弟植物感受到遠黃
In the case of more red light
紅光比較多的情況
He will tell himself to work hard to grow up
他就會告訴自己要努力長大
This is the extension of Jinmu will be faster
就是這個金木的延長就會比較快
faster results
比較快的結果
He'll grow faster than his two big brothers
他就會長得比他兩個大哥快
faster than his two older brothers
長得比他兩個大哥快
Then he has a chance to stand out
之後他就有機會突出
This so-called shade or tree layer
這個所謂的遮蔽或是樹貫層
It is more convenient for him to grow taller
長得比較高方便他
receive light for photosynthesis
接受到光線來進行光合作
sustain his own growth
維持他自己的生長
This is also a feeling of light quality
這個也是一個光品質的一個感受
wait a minute let's talk about this
等一下我們花一段時間講這個
Some regulation of light on plants
光的一些對植物的調控
Another obvious
另外還有一個很明顯
is also
就是也是
Turns out I was reading my daughter's
出現我最近在讀我女兒的
middle school biology textbook
國中的生物學課本
I also started to read about photophobia
我也開始讀到相光性
suddenly feel so kind
突然覺得好親切
I feel that I have let down my teacher a little bit.
覺得以前有點辜負老師
not so deep experience
並沒有那麼深刻的體會
So I always make my daughter
所以說我常常把我女兒做好來
Obligation to teach her to listen to this
義務要教學給她聽這樣
She just isn't always interested
她就是不見得永遠都有興趣
So one of them I saw in her textbook
所以其中一個我從她課本裡面看到的
photogenic
就是相光性
The photonity is, for example,
那相光性就是比如說
the light comes from here
光線從這邊來
Then I use it to grow long
那我用來長長長長
light came
光來了
Is to follow the angle of light, follow the direction of light, this is phase
就是追隨光的角度,追隨光的方向,這是相光性
It's mostly a blu-ray reaction
這主要是一個藍光的反應
In addition, not only plants can move, we just saw some videos of many plants moving
另外不僅植物會動,我們剛剛看到很多植物會動的一些影片
In addition to the movement of plants, the things inside the cells also move
植物會動之外,細胞裡面的東西也會動
Another great feature of plant cells is that there are karma in plant cells
植物細胞還有一個很大的特色就是植物細胞裡面有業率體
Yeshiti is a location for making photosynthesis to produce starch and soup
業率體就是製作光合作用產生澱粉跟湯類的一個位置
Inside the cell is a so-called air-filled place
在細胞裡面所謂的一個包氣的位置
This karmic body has many
這個業率體在每個細胞裡面都有很多個
The chloroplast actually moves around inside the cell
這個業率體在細胞裡面事實上也會動來動去
How to move and what direction to move are also controlled according to the light
怎麼動,用什麼方向動,也是根據光線來調控
wait a minute let's talk
等一下我們花一點時間講
In addition, plant cells also have a very special structure called stomata
另外植物細胞還有一個很特殊的構造叫做氣孔
Just like the nose, the back of each leaf on the top of the leaf
就是像鼻子一樣,每片葉子上面葉背
It has a structure with many pores
它有很多氣孔的構造
The structure of this stomata is mainly when it opens
這個氣孔的構造主要就是它打開的時候
There is a communication channel in the leaves of plants with the outside world.
植物的葉片裡面就跟外界有一個交換的管道
This exchange pipe can let the gas in as well
這個交換的管道可以讓氣體進來也可以
let the gas out
讓氣體出去
The incoming gas is carbon dioxide
進來的氣體就是二氧化碳
Can carry out photosynthesis
可以進行光合作用
Plants fix carbon dioxide to produce sugars
植物固定二氧化碳產生糖類
At the same time, the oxygen released in this process is also
同時也把在這個過程裡面釋放出來的氧氣
released into the atmosphere
釋放到大氣裡面
Workers use
工人類使用
In addition to gas exchange
除了氣體的交換之外
and some water vapor release
還有一些水蒸氣的釋放
For example, plants absorb water
比如說植物吸水
sucked too much
吸了太多了
It's the way the existing water vapor evaporates
它就是既有水蒸氣的蒸發的方式
released from the pores
從氣孔裡面釋放出來
For the water cycle
對水的循環來講
it's also important
這也很重要
such as water
比如說水
rain falls into the soil
雨水落到土壤裡面
Then it drains and then the plant roots absorb it
然後流失然後植物根部吸收起來之後
evapotranspiration through the stomata of leaves
再經過葉子的氣孔的蒸散作用
back into the atmosphere
回到大氣裡面
This also completes a water cycle
這也完成了一個水的循環
Therefore, the opening and closing of stomata are also regulated by light.
所以氣孔的開合也受到光所調控
Another wait will be the last
另外等一下也會最後
it will take a while
也會花一點時間
Let me introduce you to the so-called biological clock
跟各位介紹所謂的生物時鐘
Light also controls plant biological clocks
光線也控制了植物生物時鐘
let the plants know
讓植物知道
chicken nugget blood is also falling
雞塊血也在落掉
Its daybreak
天亮了
8:00 pm
下午晚上八點
the heat fell
熱落了
it's time to sleep
現在是要睡覺了
So it also controls the plant biological clock
所以說也控制了植物生物時鐘
This also controls the flowering time of some plants
這也連帶了控制了一些植物的開花的時間
until the final opening
一直到最後開完化之後
annual plants at this time
一年生的植物在這個時候
The leaves begin to age
葉片就會開始進入老化的程序
So from birth
所以說從出生
From germination to plant aging
就發芽之後到植物最後老化的過程
Each step is regulated by light information
這個每一步都受到光訊息的一個調控
I hope to have a chance to introduce you
等一下希望有機會跟大家介紹到
Among them, I think the part with more typical characteristics
其中我認為比較典型特徵的部分
Plants see these external light environments
植物會看到這些外在的光環境
how did you see it
是怎麼看到的
In fact, after decades of research by scientists
其實經過數十年科學家的研究
It turns out it's really easy
發現其實到底很簡單
Although plants do not have eyes that we can see
植物雖然沒有我們看得到的眼睛
but it has some special proteins
但是它有一些特殊的蛋白質
These proteins are inside the cell
這些蛋白質在細胞裡面
act as the eyes of the plant
就充當植物的眼睛
Some properties of the light environment outside can be seen
可以看到外面光環境的一些性質
For example, we just talked about
比如說我們剛剛講到
From UV light to blue light
從UV光到藍光
Green light, red light, far red light, etc.
綠光 紅光 遠紅光等等
This is distributed across the spectrum of visible light
這分佈在可見光的光譜裡面
the ultraviolet part
那紫外光的部分
there's a protein called ultraviolet light
就有一個蛋白質叫做紫外光的壽體
This was not discovered until last year
這個到一直到去年才被發現
body with ultraviolet light
有紫外光的壽體
The other body of blue light
那另外藍光的壽體
silver flower
有包含所謂的銀花色素
or phototropin
或是相光素phototropin
There is also the Red Light Garden
另外還有紅光園
The receptor for red light is called luciferin
紅光的受體叫做光明素
i want these names
我想這些名稱
Basically it doesn't mean that much
基本上它的意義並沒有那麼大的
for most
對大部分來講
That's the part I need to know
就是我需要了解的部分
it is a rate of fire
它是一個射速
it is a protein
它是一個蛋白質
Usually this protein
通常這個蛋白質
added one more
都還加了一個
so-called plankton
所謂的浮霉
or some compounds
或者是一些化合物
it will follow this protein
它會以跟這個蛋白質
by shared driving
以共駕駛的方式
tightly together
緊密的結合在一起
these compounds
這些化合物
it has many
它本身有很多的
ring structure
環狀的構造
Or this ring has a lot of double swords on it
或是這個環上面有很多的雙劍
These characteristics make these compounds
這些特徵都讓這些化合物
Has a strong knee-light quality
有很強的膝光的特質
like the clothes we wear
就像我們身上穿的衣服
concurrent example
兼舉的例子
Colored clothes worn on seat
在座身上穿的有顏色的衣服
There are some special chemical ingredients in it
裡面有些特殊化學的成分
Can absorb some special light fragments
能吸收一些特殊的光碎
rendered color
呈現出來的顏色
is its complementary color
是它的護補色
The same goes for these protein molecules
這些蛋白質分子也是一樣
It has these special structures
它因為有這些特殊的構造
with some special indirect compounds
跟一些特殊的一些間接的化合物
so that it can only accept ultraviolet light
讓它能夠特別的只接受到紫外光
Or only specifically accept blue light
或是只特別的接受到藍光
either red light or far red light
或是紅光或是遠紅光
This deck has some properties like this
這彈牌子有一些像這樣子的特性
wait we get a chance to see one of these
等一下我們有機會看到其中一個
But why on earth can it see red light or far red light
但到底為什麼它可以看到紅光或是遠紅光
Basically plants have these pigments inside the cells
基本上植物有這些色素在細胞裡面
it can be used to say
它就可以利用說
For example, I now see a blue light and two red lights
比如說我現在看到了一個藍光跟兩個紅光
Plants can understand
植物就可以解讀說好
So in my current environment
所以我現在的環境裡面
It turns out that red light comes more than blue light
原來是紅光比藍光要來得多
In this way plants can judge
利用這樣子的方式植物就可以判斷
What is the amount of red light in the environment now?
現在環境裡面到底紅光的量是多少
What is the amount of blue light
藍光的量是多少
and its bright change
以及它亮的變化
And what is the relative ratio between
還有相對之間的比例是什麼
So there can be an absolute sense
所以說可以有絕對的感應
There can also be relative induction
還可以有相對的感應
Here are a few examples
在這裡要先舉幾個例子
Ultraviolet light plants if in case there is no these
紫外光植物如果萬一沒有這些
When the eyes or chromophores can sense
可以感應的眼睛或是色素體的時候
will cause some colorblind Arabian plants
就會造成一些色盲的阿拉伯界植物
this is what i said
這是我自己講的
I guess they don't want to be adults like this
我想他們一定不願意成人是這樣
basically
基本上呢
But I think it doesn't make sense for me to say that now
可是我覺得我這樣講現在沒有道理的
I'll tell you what you think
我講講看看大家覺得怎麼樣
This is where different plants grow in the dark
這是不同的植物生長在黑暗裡面
They are all tall and long
他們都長得很高很長
The lower elbow will be extended a lot
這個下沛肘都會延長的很多
Then, Ziye will
然後呢 紫葉都會
head bent
頭都會彎彎的
See it here on Blu-ray
那在這裡看到是在藍光
These plants are grown on Blu-ray Thoughts
這個這些植物是生長在藍光思想
That's a normal plant
那這是正常的植物
It's when we don't make any moves
就是我們不要動什麼手腳的時候
Normal plants should grow like this
正常的植物就應該長這樣
In this way, I think everyone should be familiar with the eyes
這樣我想大家應該很熟悉眼光
multiple it looks like this
多個 它這樣就長這樣
So what if we made a move?
那如果說呢我們動了一個手腳
Destroy the protein that receives blue light
把它接收藍光的那個蛋白質破壞掉
at
就在
Plants are like people
植物裡面跟人一樣
There are many genes in plants
植物裡面有很多的基因
Then we know which gene is
那我們知道哪一個基因是
Made that protein specifically to receive blue light
專門做出那個蛋白質去接收藍光
After destroying that gene?
把那個基因破壞掉之後呢
will see it
就會看到它
I have seen Blu-ray, I have seen it, I have not seen it
有看到藍光有看到那沒有看到
It's just that it looks a bit like it looks in the dark
就是它長得就有點像它在黑暗時候的樣子
right
對不對
because it feels like saying
因為它就覺得說
something
某些東西
Then you can also plant
那另外你還可以對植物
do some
做一些
some processing is to say
一些處理就是說
ok i now know which blu ray receiver
好了我現在知道哪一個藍光的接受器
A receptor for blue light is the main ingredient
一個藍光的受體是主要的成分
then I'll let it do a lot in the plant
那我就讓它在植物裡面做很多
Just using the rotor is the way of genetic modification
就是利用轉子就是基因改造的方式
Let it do a lot of blue light receptors in plants
讓它在植物裡面做很多藍光的受體
Then what happens is that
那這就會發生的狀況就是
Just plants are too high, right?
就是植物就太high了對不對
it sees a lot of blue light
它就看到了很多的藍光
It thinks it sees blue light all over the world
它就以為它看到全天下的藍光
so it grows very small
所以它就長得非常矮小
That is to say, the effect of this extension is
就是說這個延長的這個效果就
too obvious
太過於顯著
So say you can see this
所以說你就可以看到這個
Then this one is what I call color
那這一個就是被我稱之為色
Then this one is too excited plant
那這一個就是太激動的植物
what about the other
那另外呢
We just mentioned that there is a
我們剛剛講到有一個是
Receptors for red and far-red light
接受紅光跟遠紅光的受體
luciferin
叫做光明素
what about after you broke it
那你把它弄壞了之後呢
it looks fine on blu ray doesn't it
它在藍光下面看起來沒什麼問題對不對
Because it's not meant to be watched on Blu-ray.
因為它本來就不是要看藍光的嘛
So after you broke it
所以說你把它弄壞了之後
it looks ok on blu ray no problem
它在藍光下面看起來OK沒什麼問題
But this plant if you put it under a red light
可是這顆植物如果你把它放到紅光之下
it won't work
它就不行了
So it can be missing for this plant
所以它可以這個植物缺少了
When looking at this red pigment
看這紅光的色素的時候
It grows no problem on blu-ray
它在藍光下面長得沒有問題
Because blue light can control the growth of plants
因為藍光可以控制植物的生長
I'm fine as long as the blue light receptors are there
我只要藍光的受體在我就OK
But I'm under the red light
可是呢我在紅光之下
I just need this gene to be broken and I'll look wrong
我只要這個基因壞掉我就長得不對勁了
On the contrary, we just said that not only you
那相反的我們剛剛講不光你把
something that receives blu ray
接收藍光的東西
reduce a lot or become a lot
減少了很多或是變得很多
It looks normal under red light
它在紅光下面看起來很正常
So there are these proteins
所以說有這些蛋白質的存在
Let me say that there are these genes and the products of these genes
讓我說有這些基因跟這些基因的產物
presence of protein
蛋白質的存在
Let the cells of this plant
讓這個植物的細胞
free to receive
可以自由自在的接收
different light
不一樣的光線
That's also because we deal with
那也由於我們藉由這樣的處理
You can process blue light or you can process red light
你可以處理藍光或者是處理紅光
to judge
來判斷
what the hell did you break it
你到底把它弄壞的那個東西
what is the response of the cells it dominates
它所主宰的細胞的反應是什麼
So it's Blu-ray's hands and heels
所以說是藍光的手體跟
red hand
紅光的手體
Then the Arabic knot that shoots mans after falling off
那後來掉了之後就射芒的阿拉伯結
So you can't see blue light and you can't see red light.
所以是看不到藍光跟看不到紅光的
arabian knot plant
阿拉伯結植物
good
好
what's next
那接下來呢
I'm going to take a moment to introduce you to
我要跟各位花點時間來介紹一下
Plant Response to Red Light
植物對紅光的反應
The ones I circled now are all plants
這些我現在圈起來的這些都是植物
Things to do when exposed to red light
照到紅光之後會做的事情
it would love to sprout it would love
它會喜歡發芽 它會喜歡
The leaves are opened, and then I accompany you around for a short time
植葉打開 然後下陪走遍短
it will feel in fact feel
它會感受到 事實上是感受到
The ratio of red light to far red light will grow taller
紅光遠紅光的比例 它會長得比較高
It will have a biological clock, it will promote flowering and so on
它會有生物時鐘 它會促進開花等等
let's take a moment to talk
我們花一點點時間來講
why and how
為什麼可以這樣 還有怎麼做到的
This is a recap of what we just saw
這個就是複習一下我們剛剛看到的
I think you should be very familiar with it by now.
我想大家現在已經 應該已經非常熟悉
Grow in the dark and under the light
在黑暗跟在 照光下面生長
There is a very electrical characteristic that
有一個很電型的特徵就是
The back of the shrimp is short and the leaves are opened, right?
蝦背走遍短 植葉打開 對不對
I'm going to tell you what I just said
那我要 我剛剛跟各位講說
It has some different light receptors
它有一些不一樣光的受體
we all know how it came to be
我們都知道它是怎麼來
but at first
但是最一開始的時候
how did you find these things
是怎麼找到這些東西
That is to say, I will tell you now
就是說 我現在講給你聽
I am also very good at opera. I have studied it over the past few decades.
我戲曲也很 過去數十年研究的
Sun Moon Essence
日月精華
I will tell you a conclusion
我跟大家講一個結論
But at the very beginning
可是在最開始的時候是
how did biologists or botanists find this thing
生物學家或植物學家是怎麼找到這個東西的
This is just as important as the external form we observed at the beginning
這就跟我們一開始觀察的外部的形態就很重要
We know that normal seedlings should grow under the light, right?
我們知道說正常的用苗應該在光照下面長這樣對不對
Now I want to know which gene in which cell is controlling this process
那我現在想要知道說到底是哪一個細胞裡面哪一個基因在控制這個過程
So one way I, a botanist, can do is to use genetic methods to study this technology
所以我植物學家可以做一個方式就是利用遺傳的方式來研究這個科技
The example given here is to say
在這裡為大家舉的例子就是說
I know plants grow like this when exposed to light
我知道植物照光之後會長這樣
then i can imagine
那我也可以想像
If the plant lacks the condition of sensing the external light environment,
如果植物缺少了這個感應外在光環境的這個條件之後
After a gene is broken
一個基因壞掉之後
my plants might grow like this
我的植物就可能會長這樣
For example, if I stay with you, it will last longer
比如說我下陪著就會長比較長
I can't shorten
我沒有辦法縮短
Or it means that my cotyledons cannot develop a good karma body
或者是說我的子葉就沒有辦法發育良好的業率體
I become more yellow, right?
我就變得比較黃對不對
So I have this idea
所以說我就有這個這樣的想法
when in my heart
在心中的時候呢
I started doing some mutations on these seeds
我就開始對這些種子做一些突變的處理
Usually dealing with some right-handed agents to allow some mutations in his genes
通常處理一些右邊劑讓他的基因能夠產生一些突變
When a gene mutation is severe enough, the gene is destroyed
基因產生突變到夠嚴重的時候這個基因就會被破壞
when it's broken
破壞的時候呢
Let's say we just destroyed luminin
比如說我們剛破壞了光明素
he can't see the red light
他就看不到紅光
Destroyed some flowering trees so he couldn't see the blu-ray and so on
破壞了一些引花樹他就看不到藍光等等
So after dealing with the right agent?
所以處理完右邊劑之後呢
You can put his purple belt on the spider
你可以把他的紫帶的蜘蛛呢
grow in light
在光照下面生長
then look for those
然後找尋那些
look different
看起來長不大一樣的
looks very tall
看起來長得特別高的
or look particularly yellow
或是看起來特別黃的
These plants may contain
這些植物裡面可能就包含
The gene that has the photoreceptor we want to study is affected by some
有我們想要研究的光收體的基因受到了一些
destruction and mutation
破壞跟突變
To study where these genes are bad
去研究這些基因到底壞在什麼地方
Where is the damage in the nucleus?
到底壞在細胞核的什麼位置
what gene is broken
什麼基因壞掉
These can be studied by some methods of molecular biology
這些可以經由一些分子生物學的研究的方法
Find out what's wrong with him
去找出來他到底壞在哪裡
After finding it
找到了之後呢
we can
我們就可以
Basically, a simple conclusion for everyone is that
基本上跟大家一個簡單的結論就是
this is white light
這是白光
This is what we just saw in normal growth
這是我們剛看到的正常的生長的情況
There are two mutations of luciferin seen here
在這裡有看到兩個光明素的突變
A so-called mutant strain
一個是所謂的突變株
Bright tree A is under the far red light
光明樹A它就是在遠紅光下面
it just looks like under the dark
它就是長得跟在黑暗下面一樣
The other one is Bright Tree B
那另外一個是光明樹B
it grows under red light
它長在紅光下面
Looks like it just grows longer than in the dark
看起來就是長得比在黑暗的時候還要長
So one can't see the red light
所以一個看不到紅光
One cannot see far red light
一個看不到遠紅光
So in this way to find the corresponding gene
所以藉由這樣的方式去找出相對應的基因
which gene
到底是哪一個基因
Figure out which protein is receiving the light
做出哪一個蛋白質在接受這些光線
That
那
without these
如果沒有這些
Kyodo grows taller
景多長得比較高
It's a good thing you won't die like this
好意思就是不會死這樣
but in fact it will
可是事實上會
it will have some serious repercussions
它會有一些很嚴重的影響
For example this is
比如說這個是
Normal curve length this home has started to bloom
正常的彎道長這家已經開始開花了
Then if the corner does not have the gene of Bright Tree A
那如果彎道沒有光明樹A的這個基因的時候
You will find that it just keeps growing leaves
你就會發現它就是不停的長葉子
it won't bloom either
它也不會開花
If it doesn't bloom, we don't have bean shells to eat, right?
不會開花我們就沒有豆甲可以吃對不對
So this has a big impact
所以說這個影響很大
what about the other
那另外呢
tomato
番茄
normal tomato it has started to turn green
正常的番茄它已經開始變綠
Then you can harvest it when it turns red
然後等著要變紅就可以採收
that's normal
那當這個正常的
When I took this tomato mutant to Guangming Tree A and B
把這個番茄的突變株去找光明樹A跟B的時候
because it looks great
因為它圖長得很厲害
This receptacle cannot develop normally
這個攝素體沒有辦法正常的發育
So say there are lifted some white tomatoes
所以說有解除一些白番茄
Probably a rare one in Japan
可能在日本來講是一個稀有的
popular varieties
受歡迎的品種
But this is also a big sacrifice in terms of production.
但是這個對產量來講也是一個很大的犧牲
So when these luminophores do not exist,
所以說沒有這些光明素存在的時候
Indeed, in addition to making plants grow taller,
的確除了讓植物長得比較高之外
There are many follow-up pairs on production
還有很多後續的對產量上
Some effects on some growth
對一些生長上的一些影響
In addition
另外呢
also a lot of fun
也是一個很有趣
It is also a classic experiment
也是一個很經典的實驗
That is to say, I thought about it for a long time and couldn't give up.
就是說我想了半天沒有辦法捨棄
I decided to explain this matter to everyone.
這件事情決定還是要跟大家說明一下
This is a
這是一個
looks like a photobiologist studying
就長得光生物學家在研究
A very classic experiment in the development of light
光的發育的時候一個很經典的實驗
It's an experiment to germinate or not to germinate
就是發芽還是不發芽的實驗
This is an experiment with a grip seed
這是一個握具種子的實驗
It is also observed in nature
它也是觀察到自然界裡面
as if there were some rays between
好像有一些光線之間
There are some phenomena of mutual relief
有一些互相解康的現象
For example, this grip seed is in the dark
比如說這個握具種子在黑暗的時候
it has a poor germination rate
它就有發芽率很差
When you see white soil coming out, that's the germination.
你看到白色土出來那個才是發芽
after the red light
照了紅光之後
sprouted well
發芽發得很好
But what about this naughty scientist
可是呢這個頑皮的科學家
After the red light was illuminated, the far red light was illuminated
照了紅光之後又照了遠紅光
far red light
就追加遠紅光
Then I found that it didn't germinate again.
然後發現又不發芽了
Of course we're adding a dose of red light, right?
當然就在追加一劑紅光對不對
sprouted again
又發芽了
Then add another round light and it won't sprout again.
然後再加一個圓光又不發芽了
So this is the boring science
所以這個就是很疲的那個科學
But this leads to a very important discovery
可是這帶來一個很重要的一個發現
It means that there is a rate of fire in the cell
就表示說在細胞裡面有一個射速
or have two rates of fire
或是有兩個射速
Inside the cells it receives messages of red light
在細胞裡面它會接收紅光的訊息
will also receive messages from the round red light
也會接收圓紅光的訊息
Then these two things will counteract each other
那這兩個東西會互相解抗
Let's see what was the last message you received
那看你最後收到的訊息是什麼
Or turn the lights on, turn off the lights, turn on the lights, turn off the lights, turn on the lights, turn off the lights, turn on the lights
或是開燈關燈開燈關燈開燈關燈開燈
Of course I knew to turn on the light
當然就知道要開燈
So in the processing of the red light and the round red light
那所以說在這個紅光跟圓紅光的處理
basically telling the seeds of these diggers
基本上就在告訴這些挖具的種子
Are you going to sprout now or not?
你現在是要發芽還是不發芽
What was the last signal you received?
那看你最後收到的那個訊號是什麼
It is what determines what the digging seed will do.
就是決定了這個挖具種子要做的事情
This is a very classic lighting treatment
這是一個很經典的光照處理
An example of seed growth and development
對種子生長跟發育的一個例子
That luciferin itself is a very beautiful protein
那光明素本身是一個非常漂亮的蛋白質
That's when I was doing my Ph.D.
就是我在念博士辦的時候
I'm just studying this luminosin
就是在研究這個光明素
this pigment
這個色素
If you have a way to store this pigment out of the cells
這個色素如果說你有辦法把它從細胞裡面存化出來
easy to put in water
放在水裡方容易
when put in water
就是放在水裡面的時候
It's a very nice teal an easy
它是一個非常漂亮的藍綠色的一個容易
Then see if it is absorbing red light or
那看它是在吸收紅光還是在
A form that absorbs red light or a form that absorbs red light
一個吸收紅光的形式還是吸收紅光的形式
Then you know this teal is a little bit different
那您知道這個藍綠色稍微有一點點不一樣
very beautiful color
非常美麗的顏色
So sometimes doing research work
所以說有時候做研究工作
It's like my own research in molecular biology
就是像我自己從事分子生物學的研究
I'm always researching things I can't see
常常都在研究一些看不到的東西
That's us in the test tube
就是我們在試管裡面
some experiments done
所做的一些實驗
often do not know what to do
常常不知道在做什麼
because too small
因為太小了
so eyes can't see
所以眼睛看不到
other methods of analysis are required to see
必須要借助其他分析方法才可以看到
Therefore, it is possible to see the quality of a protein with ulterior motives.
所以說能夠有用心看到一個蛋白質分質如此的
The color is so beautiful
就是顏色是上色澤如此的美麗
This is also a great condition for research work
這也是在研究工作上面一個很大的條件
Then I want to tell you why I can see light
那接下來要跟各位講為什麼我可以看到光線
not because i'm here
並不是因為我在這裡
This is my doctor class teacher
這個是我博士班的老師
His name is Clark Beggar and he is also in the University of California to share
他叫做Clark Beggar也是在加州大學的大衛生分享
Then why did he let
那他是讓為什麼
The book of light can see the light
光明書可以看到光線這件事情
able to have a theoretical explanation
能夠有一個學理上的解釋
a very important scientist
一個很重要的科學家
This is in the Forbidden City
這個是在故宮
After returning to work in Taiwan
就是回來台灣工作之後
Once he came to Taiwan to visit us
有一次他來台灣看我們
like looking at his own child
就像看他自己的小孩
own new toy
自己的新的玩具
when there is a new laboratory
有一個新的實驗室的時候
come care about us
來關心我們
Then his discovery is actually very simple
那他的發現其實很簡單
just like I just introduced to you
就是像我剛剛跟大家介紹
last protein
最後一個蛋白質
If he connects a pigment molecule
他如果連了一個色素分子
Then he can see the light
之後他就可以看到光線
this gene
這個基因
Genes of most materials
大部分資物的基因
made in the nucleus
在細胞核裡面製作
inside the nucleus
在細胞核裡面
The nucleus will pass through some
細胞核就會經過一些
The Process of Molecular Biology
分子生物學的過程
molecules that make proteins
製造出蛋白質的分子
that protein molecule
那這個蛋白質分子
Can't feel light by itself
本身並沒有辦法感光
To be sensitive to light, it must accept
它要感光必須要接受到
some its called some
一些它的所謂的一些
Today he draws almost
今天他畫乎
After my co-drilling union with him
我跟他進行共鑽間的結合之後
The whole combination of co-drilling
那這整個共鑽間的結合
contains this chromatophore
包含了這個色素體
itself with protein
本身跟蛋白質在一起
form a special structure
形成一個特殊的構造
This structure is able to absorb very accurate red light
這構造才能夠吸很準的紅光
Accurate round red light
跟很準的圓紅光
This rate of fire itself is created inside the karmic body
這個射速本身是在業力體裡面製造的
So a very important discovery with Cocker-U.S.
所以跟Cocker-U.S.很重要的一個發現
is to determine the structure of this
就是決定出這個的結構
This velocity body is four annular
這個射速體就是四個環狀
This structure with a lot of shoulders on it
上面有很多雙肩的這個結構
It is mainly to solve the structure
它是主要解出這個結構
After solving this structure, let us also understand it
解出這個結構之後也讓我們了解它
Why is this fire rate molecule itself able to see light
為什麼這個射速分子本身可以看得到光線
This is a very important contribution of it
這是它一個很重要的貢獻
This is an analysis of the absorption spectrum
這個是一個吸收光譜的分析
tell us because wait there's another absorption spectrum
告訴我們因為等一下還有一張吸收光譜
So I want to use this one to introduce to you first
所以我想用這張先跟大家介紹一下
The horizontal axis of this graph is a wavelength
這張圖的橫軸是一個波長
is from 300 to 800
就是從300到800
We just said that visible light ranges from about 400 to 800
我們剛剛講可見光大概從400到800左右
Then the heavy axis is an absorbance value
那這個重軸是一個吸光值
so I can absorb that particular wavelength of light
所以我可以吸收那個特殊波長的光
A little more of this waveform is a little higher
多一點的這個波形就高一點
So you can see that it has parts that absorb red light
所以說你可以看到它有吸收紅光的部分
also absorb far-red light
也有吸收遠紅光
It mostly does not absorb yellow or green light
它大部分不會吸收黃色或是綠色的光線
that is to say it is a rate of fire
就是說這是一個射速
This is a light hand with a velocity body
這是一個光的手體加上射速體之後
a property of itself
它本身的一個性質
Just now we told the story of two older brothers and one younger brother
剛剛我們有講到兩個大哥一個小弟的故事
It was when I grew up in Shayin Lane
就是長在遮陰巷的時候
Plants grow normally under light
植物在光照下它是長得正常的
internode size leaf spread
節間的大小葉片展開
But if there are many brothers and sisters next to it
可是它旁邊如果有很多兄弟姊妹
It is said that many seeds are walking together
說是很多種子散步在一起
when he sprouted together
他一起萌芽的時候
He will start to have some competition and some confrontation than plants grow
他比植物生長就會開始產生一些競爭跟一些對立
At this point I think it's obvious that
這時候我想很明顯的就是
He will feel that the environment is not suitable
他會感受到環境並不適合
It's not like he grew up in full sun
並不像他長在完全的日照下面的情況
what happened at this time
這個時候到底發生了什麼事情
So we are not plants
所以說我們不是植物
we don't know what he was thinking
我們不知道他念念到什麼
But we can also machine can measure
但是我們也可以機器可以測量
What is the current spectrum for plants
到底現在的光譜對植物來講
what is it like
到底是什麼樣子
For example, this orange line
比如說這條橘子色的線
It's the spectrum under the sun
就是在太陽光底下面的光譜
Traveling sideways is the same wavelength
橫走一樣是波長
Vertically, these different wavelengths of light
縱走是這些不同的波長的光
how much is it
它的量到底有多少
so under the sun
所以在太陽光之下
You can see most of it will be on Blu-ray
你可以看到大部分會是在藍光以上
Then there are many parts of red light and far red light
然後紅光遠紅光的部分很多
What does the little brother under the big brother feel?
那個大哥下面的小弟他感受到是什麼
It's the blue one, it's the green one
是藍色的這一條,是綠色的這一條
The green one you will find the plants under the green leaf print
綠色的這一條你會發現在綠葉印下面的植物
The waveform he felt was very different from that under the sun
他感受到的波形跟在太陽光底下有很大的不相同
The most different part is that he lacks a lot of red parts
其中最不相同的地方就是他缺乏了很多紅光的部分
Part of this red light has been absorbed by the leaves below
這紅光的部分因為已經被下面的葉子吸收了
The leaves are green, so most of his absorption is his
葉子是綠色,所以他大部分吸收是他的
Complementary color, red light
護補色、紅色的光線
Then when making light and making light, some very efficient long light
然後在做光和做光,非常有效率的一些破長的光線
So the situation he feels here is
所以他在這裡感受到的狀況就是
The ratio of red light to far red light under sunlight will be greater than 1
太陽光下面紅光比遠紅光的比例會大於1
Most of it is red light, a small part is far red light
大部分是紅光,少部分是遠紅光
Most of the light below the green leaf print is far red light, and a small part is red light
在綠葉印下面大部分是遠紅光,少部分是紅光
So his ratio is less than 1
所以他的比例就小於1
We just mentioned that there is a luciferin pigment molecule in the cell
我們剛剛講到細胞裡面有一個光明素的色素分子
He can receive red light and far red light, right?
他可以接收紅光跟遠紅光對不對
So he can receive red light and far red light
所以他可以接收紅光跟遠紅光
he can detect the ratio between the two
他就可以偵測這兩個之間的比例
what ratio is there now
現在有什麼比例
How much is the red light? How much is the original red light?
紅光竟然是多少 原紅光竟然是多少
When my original red light became so much
我原紅光變得這麼多的時候
I have no choice but to grow faster
沒辦法我只好長快一點
I'll have a chance to spit it out sooner.
那長快一點我就有機會可以吐出來
right
對不對
This is one use for detecting the ratio between this red light and the original red light
這就是偵測這個紅光跟原紅光之間比例的一個用處
What about such a phenomenon?
那這樣的一個現象呢
Also known as a response to shade avoidance
也叫做遮陰迴避的一個反應
Or called shareable is a bit of a description
或是叫做shareable有點形容
the shade avoidance response
那遮陰迴避反應
that often has some negative
那常常會有一些負面
There will be some negative situations for plants
對植物來講會有一些負面的情況
Because it is already a last resort for plants to grow under such conditions
因為植物長在那種情況之下已經很不得已的
right
對不對
so it has to pay something
所以它必須要付出一些代價
and let it grow faster
然後讓它自己能夠長得比較快
what does it cost
它的代價是什麼
The price is often this because the extension is very long
代價常常就是這個因為延長得很長
it blooms early
它會提早開花
Or the plants bloom early
或者說植物提早開花
Early flowering often has many disadvantages
提早開花常常有很多缺點
Because I haven't got enough energy to go bare metal
因為我還沒有裸機到足夠的能量
So I may be outdated and not good in the future
所以我之後可能結的過時也結的不好
I don't plant enough seeds
我結的種子也結的不夠多
My plants are not strong enough
我的植物不夠強壯
That may be for some, such as this carrot
那或者是對一些比如說這個蘿蔔
This one is very extended
這個延長得很厲害
Just to feel more far-red light
就是要感受到遠紅光比較多
Chinese its output is not very good
中文它的產量也沒有很好
So this excessive masking of the currency response
所以說這個過度的遮蔽匯幣反應
May have some negative effects on plants
可能對植物會帶來一些負面的影響
but
但是呢
there are always many things
凡是總是很多事情
How you see things determines how you react
你看事情的觀點會決定你要怎麼反應
So let's say an interesting scientist
所以說有一個有趣的科學家
His name is Pearson Song
他叫做皮爾遜宋
He was born earlier in the United States
他之前早點生在美國的
that's not university
那不是大學
And now at Kyushu University
然後現在在寄州果立大學
this one
是這一位
That was once he went to Taiwan
那就是有一次他到台灣
It should have been made at the Interpretation Center.
應該是在傳譯中心製作了一查
Then he has a different view on this matter
那他對這件事情就有一些不一樣的看法
I also think it's quite interesting
那我也覺得也蠻有趣的
Share it with everyone
跟大家分享一下
he took advantage of this
他利用了這個
Avoid this effect of shading
迴避遮蔭的這個效應
He wants to make a new plant
他想要去製作一個新的植物
Then this plant is very useful.
那這個植物有些很實用上面的
to consider
考量
and then introduce
然後跟大家介紹一下
If we had a piece at home
如果說大家曾經家裡有一塊
Might be more difficult in Taipei
可能在台北比較困難
say you have a turf
就說你有一塊草皮
then you need to weed often
那你需要常常除草
that turf
那草皮都
grow fast, right?
長得很快對不對
And the turf has a feature that's what we just saw
而且草皮有一個特徵是我們剛剛看到的是什麼
It means brothers and sisters grow very close, right?
就是兄弟姐妹都長得很靠近對不對
You used your turf thick enough next to you didn't you?
你用你的草皮夠濃密你旁邊是不是
The grass must grow very densely
草都要發得很密
When the hair is very thick, do I often feel
那發得很密的時候是不是我常常會覺得
I'm too dense, I need to grow faster
我太密了我要長快一點
i want to grow longer
我要長長一點
If you want to weed, you have to work harder
那你如果是要除草又要除得更勤勞一點
then you have to think more
那你就要思維思得更多一點
To be able to grow green, right?
才能夠長得綠油油對不對
So this skimming society has a very good idea
所以這個撇書社會它就有一個非常好的想法
He said
他說
If you plant is using
你如果植物是利用
More far-red light is detected
偵測到遠紅光比較多
I'll make it grow faster
我去讓它長得比較快
With these shadowing effects
有這些遮蔽效應的話
If you avoid the effect of shading
躲避遮蔭的效應的話
i make it invisible
我就讓它看不到
I just make it impossible to feel this
我就讓它沒有辦法感受到這個
there's no way to feel this
那沒有辦法感受到這個呢
it says it has making turf
它比如說它有製作草皮
it has a genetically modified turf plant
它有一個基因改造的草皮植物
It can make plants feel
它就可以讓植物感受
Although it grows very crowded next to it
它雖然旁邊長得很擁擠
But it doesn't feel that it feels so much
可是它並不覺得它感受到有那麼多的
far red light environment
遠紅光的環境
what about this time
那個這時候呢
so I
我就
After I finished the production yesterday, it happened that I wrote it as a oil silk
我昨天打完製作之後我就發生了一把寫成一個打油絲了
that is, it grows more slowly
就是它會生長比較慢
So you don't need to make a lot of noise
所以你不需要很其鬧地去出草
it grows slower
它會生長比較慢
So its color will also
所以它的顏色也會
because it grows slower
因為長得比較慢
slow growing
長得慢的表率
because it also doesn't have some
因為它也沒有一些
Some Behaviors of Pest Prevention Industry Development
防害業率體發育的一些行為
That's because the ones that grow slowly belong to your fertilizer
那因為長得慢的屬於你肥料
Use less and be more environmentally friendly
用的比較少比較環保
So what?
所以說呢
everything has two sides
就是凡事有兩面
just look at
就是說看看
you know so i think
你知道的所以說我覺得
When an interesting phenomenon like this is
當一個諸如此類有趣的一個現象就是
After a biological phenomenon I learned
我了解的一個生物現象之後
There is really infinite room for imagination
真是有無窮廣泛的想像的空間
Be around for years
身邊信守年來
look what's going on
你看看有什麼樣子的狀況
is that you can apply what you have learned
是你可以應用學到的知識
Intermorphic observed phenomena
互形觀察到的現象
can improve your environment
可以去改善你環境裡面的
Or maybe it will help someone else
或是可能會對其他人帶來一些幫助
it's an interesting sanity
這是一個有趣的理智
Should have started on Send Away
應該已經開始在寄走島
has started in the wild
已經開始在野外
start planting
開始進行栽種
Speaking of Hongguang
那講到宏光
I would like to take a moment to introduce to you
我想也花一點時間跟大家介紹一下
Plant Response to Blue Light
植物對藍光的反應
What about the blue light?
那藍光的反應呢
there are many
也有很多
For example, the seedling growth we just talked about
比如說我們剛剛講的幼苗生長
Phase light, movement of karmic body
相光性、業率體的移動
Opening and closing of stomata, etc.
氣孔的開閉等等
These are the reactions to blue light
這些都是受到藍光的反應
That
那
First look at the power of a blue light response
先來看一下一個藍光反應的力量
that is
就是
in the middle
中間呢
these are some corn
這些是一些玉米的
grown from corn
玉米生長出來的
This is supposed to be the tooth sheath
這個是應該是牙鞘
The leaves haven't grown yet
葉片還沒長出來
A fluorescent lamp was lit in the middle
中間點了一場日光燈
All the sheaths of everyone adore it
大家所有的牙鞘都對它產生崇拜
so it's typical
所以說這是很典型的
phase light type
相光型
This example is just an enlarged illustration
這張例子只是一個放大的說明
Here is a more classic example
這是一個更經典的例子
So this picture you will see
所以這張圖片你會看到
blu ray from slice
藍光從slice的
come in from the right
右邊進來
You can see that the corn sheath grows on
大家看到這個玉米牙鞘長在
inside a small room
一個小室館裡面
this corn tooth wall will be like
這個玉米牙牆會像
blue light temperature zone
藍光偏溫區
This is the phase light type
這是相光型
it's here
在這裡
Except what we just saw was
除了我們剛剛看的是
a single career corn
一個單職業玉米
There are also some dual career plants
另外還有一些雙職業植物
like sunflower
比如像是香日葵
In this light you will see
在這張你會看到的光線
will be from here
會是從這邊來
So after it grows some albino seedlings
所以它長了一些白化的苗之後
everyone sees these
大家看到這些
cute little corn tooth
可愛的小玉米牙
You can see a lot of listeners are starting to bend to the left as well
可以看到很多聽眾也開始向左邊彎曲
So say bend to the left
所以說向左邊彎曲
At the same time, some sharp-eyed people may also encounter
那同時可能有些眼尖的也遇到
While this bend
在這個彎曲的同時
its careers are starting to open
它的職業也開始打開
Also began to develop, also began to change
也開始發育 也開始變率
So not only red light but also blue light
所以說不僅紅光 藍光
Also allows the plant to start the development of the wild aluminum body
也可以讓植物開始進行野鋁體的發育
who found this
那誰發現了這件事
or whoever found that answer
或是誰找到那個答案
why plants hang out
為什麼植物會相逛
Let me introduce this to you by the way
這個要跟各位順便介紹一下
So take this opportunity today
所以今天也趁這個機會
let me introduce
跟大家介紹一下
A few scientists who were very surprised in my heart
我心中非常驚訝的幾位科學家
They are in the phenomenon of these very interesting creatures
他們在這些很有趣的生物的現象裡面
the scientist who found the answer
找到了答案的科學家
So this guy's called Winstall Briggs
那這個人叫做Winstall Briggs
He is now at Stanford University
他是現在在斯坦福大學
Although he is very old
他雖然年紀很大
He is a member of the American Academy of Sciences
他是美國科學院院士
Those 18 years old are still very
那18幾歲還非常的
Self-reliant in research work Very dynamic
自立於研究工作 非常的有活力
he was in taiwan once
他有一次在台灣
Buy your own ticket and go to Neiwan
自己買車票就去內灣了
I'm catching a plane in Taipei
就是我在台北趕著機
Then he went to Neiwan
然後他就去內灣了
Then there is also a way in the middle
然後中間也有辦法
Go to the store to order food
到小店裡面點菜
warmly received
受到很熱誠的寬待
Very very nice this is his wife Bara
非常非常好 這是他的太太Bara
This is the ceramic wave tube we had in the gorge once
這是有一次我們在山峽的陶瓷波管
He's the one who found out why
他就是那個發現了為什麼會轉
Why is the person who shines
為什麼會相光的那個人
found that protein
找到了那個蛋白質
how did he find it
他是怎麼找到的
It is just like the method we just introduced to use 1 string
就是跟我們剛剛有介紹到利用1串的方法
After mutating the seeds of the plant
把植物的種子突變之後
Then let him see the blue light without turning his head
然後讓他看到藍光之後也不轉頭了
found the mutant
找到了這個突變株
Look at these normal seedlings
你看就是這些正常的幼苗
After Blu-ray comes
藍光過來之後
how much they bend
他們彎曲得多厲害
The speed of light of a single Blu-ray can be engineered
可以設計一個單一的藍光的光速
so he'll make an almost 90 degree turn
所以他會成一個幾乎90度的轉彎
These mutant seedlings
這些被突變的幼苗
After the three elections, these are unmoved
三選出來之後這些是不為所動的
Seedlings unmoved by blue light
對藍光不為所動的幼苗
Then Winsor & Brakes went back to study
那Winsor & Brakes回去研究了
In these mutant seedlings
到底在這些突變的幼苗裡面
After which gene is broken
到底是哪一個基因壞掉之後
found the so-called phase light number of this protein
找到了所謂相光數的這個蛋白質
It is responsible for sensing the direction of blue light
就是負責感受到藍光來的方向
and greet it
而且迎接它
Apart from
除了
like light beams to make plants feel
像光束去讓植物能夠感受到
The direction of the blue light
藍光來的方向
The wavelength of blue light has a direction other than the direction it comes from
藍光的波長還有來的方向之外
In addition, blue light also controls a very important phenomenon
另外藍光還控制一個很重要的現象
It is the so-called Ye Luji's movement
就是所謂葉律璣的移動
The displacement of Ye Luji in the cell
葉律璣在細胞裡面的移位
Ye Luji is inside the cell
葉律璣在細胞裡面
So small, take good care of your muscles
那麼小的把肌肉看好
That is, how does he move in the cell
就是說他在細胞裡面怎麼移動
And what is the purpose and purpose of moving
還有移動的用意跟目的是什麼
Let's take a look at this picture
我們來看一下這張圖
you can imagine
大家就可以想像
it's a cell
這是一個細胞的
For example, if you look at this leaf
比如說你看著這個葉片
Of course the cells are small
上面當然細胞很小
You can not see it
你看不到
This is a magnified view below the microscope
這是在顯微間下面放大的圖
this block
這一個區塊
represent individual cells
就代表一個一個的細胞
I saw a steamed bun inside
裡面看到一個像饅頭一樣
Tangyuan like buns
一個一個包子一樣的湯圓
That's Ye Luji
那就是葉律璣
So inside each plant cell
所以在每個植物細胞裡面
It has a lot of leaves
它都有非常多的葉率體
Dozens of leaf bodies
好幾十個葉率體
There are also some like inside the cells of green algae
也有一些像綠藻細胞裡面
only one large fat leafy body
只有一個很大肥胖的葉率體
Therefore, the type and number of chloroplasts are not the same
所以葉率體的種類跟樹木不大一樣
In this post you are the leaf cells of duckweed
在這個植物你這是浮平的葉片細胞
You can see that there are a lot of chloroplasts in it
你可以看到裡面有非常多的葉率體
This leaf body is in the dark
這個葉率體在黑暗的時候
It just floats around freely in the sun
它就到處漂浮自由自在的場陽
inside the cytoplasm
在細胞質裡面
in dim blue light
在微弱藍光的時候
It's actually easier to float up
它其實比較容易浮上來
able to float to the surface of this leaf
能夠浮到這個葉的表面
conceivable leaf rate body
可以想像葉率體
If it is an institution where Qingjingguang's cooperation is very important
如果是清晶光合作很重要的機構
Of course it wants to receive as much light as possible
它當然希望能夠盡量的接收光線
when the light is very weak
光線來得很微弱的時候
Of course I'm going to try my best to get to the front
我當然要盡其可能的擠到前面去
can then receive light
然後可以接收光線
But when the light comes
可是當光線來的時候
the light is strong
光線是很強的
Strong enough to form some free machines inside the cell
強到可以在細胞裡面形成一些自由機
When some structures inside the cells are destroyed
破壞細胞裡面一些構造的時候
Then they will hide
這時候它們就會躲了
It's just the beginning of the leaf body
就是葉率體就開始
well maybe too much
好了 也許太多了
Let's send some stations up front
我們派幾個站到前面好了
Others we just hide behind and take a rest
其他我們就躲在後面休息一下
So its not that the karma in these cells is relatively small.
所以說這些並不是這些細胞裡面的業率體比較少
It is the karmic body in these cells
而是這些細胞裡面的業率體
In fact, they are all ranked behind the first karma body.
事實上都排到第一個業率體的後面去了
So this is called an act of avoidance
所以這就叫做一個躲避的一個行為
That's when your current light is too strong to cause harm
就是當你光現在的太強會造成危害的時候
there are some evasive behaviors
就有一些躲避的行為
it's the act of gathering
這是聚集的行為
it's evasive behavior
這是躲避的行為
good
好
that is to find this
那是找到這個
another great scientist
另外一個偉大的科學家
is a scientist who finds it very interesting
是覺得非常有趣的科學家
This one is called Masami Zhu Wada
這個叫做Masami Zhu Wada
Mr. Wada
Wada-Sensei
He is at Kyushu University in Japan
他是在日本的九州大學
That's also a coincidence
那這也是一個很抽巧的事
It's at Yingge's Tatsubou Pavilion
是在英哥的Tatsubou館
this is his wife
這是他的太太
Let's see how he did an experiment
那我們來看一下他做了一個實驗
wait a minute you will see a video
等一下各位會看到一個影片
How many cells are there in this movie
這個影片裡面有幾個細胞
then you will see a flash
然後你會看到一個閃光
what about the flash
那個閃光呢
is the speed of light of a faint blue light
就是一個微弱的藍光的光速
The speed of light is very small
那這個光速很小
roughly smaller than a cell
大概就比一個細胞小
He will see a blue light at the speed of light
他會看到一個藍光的遠的光速
Then after you see this beam, you will see the Lunar Luna
那你們看到這個光束之後,你們會看到月綠體
would have been scattered at the edge of the cell
本來是散佈在細胞的邊緣
You will see the lunar green body slowly move into this light beam
就會看到月綠體慢慢的移動到這個光束裡面
let's take a look
我們來看一下
that's a lot of cells
這是很多的細胞
Then, you saw that the one that flickered just now was not dazzled
然後呢,你看到剛剛有一閃的那個不是眼花
really it has a beam
真的,它有一個光束
The lunar green bodies you see are concentrated here
你看到的月綠體就集中到這裡來了
So it has an accumulation response
所以它有一個accumulation response
It is a phenomenon that it will be close to Vietnam light
就是它會像越南光靠攏的一個現象
again
再一次
We see the Luna and then we see the blue light here
我們看到月綠體,然後看到藍光在這裡
Then, the lunar chlorophyll will see, the blue light is coming, hurry up
然後,月綠體就會看,藍光來了,趕快
ok so hurry on over here
好,所以趕快繼續到這邊來
So it's a clustering phenomenon
所以說這是一個聚集的現象
The same thing, if the blue light you see is very strong blue light
那同樣的呢,如果看到的這個藍光是很強的藍光
What will happened?
會發生什麼事?
will avoid, yes
就會避開,對
So many months of etiquette will start to hide aside
所以很多月的禮儀就會開始躲到旁邊去
So, just some blu-rays
所以說,就是一些藍光
According to Strong Meat, I hope you can really agree
根據強肉會希望你們可以真正的說好
Now I come with a few photons
現在我來的是幾個光子
Most of the time, I just let go
多的時候呢,我就散開
Be active when you are young
少的時候就積極過來
so know how to go
所以懂得去
Extremely must chest
居極必胸
This Blu-ray portable
這藍光的手提
This person is in the audience
這個人在觀眾群裡面
this is my daughter
這是我的女兒
So this is someone who just got through
所以這個是剛剛通了一個人
Mr. Wada
Wada Sensei
So why did you suddenly show this picture?
那這是為什麼要突然秀這張圖片呢
In fact, I want to spend a lot
事實上跟我想花多多
Take a minute to introduce these two adorable scientists
花個一分鐘介紹這兩位心目中之一可愛的科學家
what about the scientists
那科學家呢
he has a very dynamic personality
他個性非常的有活力
very interesting
非常的有趣
He waits for some Sly to introduce
他等一下有幾張史萊來介紹
why he enjoys research work as he enjoys life
為什麼他享受研究工作如享受人生
The source of this picture is actually very interesting
那這張圖片事實上來源很有趣
Just one time we had a photobiology meeting at home
就是有一次我們在家中開一個光生物學的會議
Those who attended were all famous
那其中與會的都是著名的
or a paid self-care photobiologist
或是有所賺償的自護光生物學家
what about my daughter
那我的女兒呢
Usually I've been conscripted everywhere since I was a kid
通常從小到大就跟我四處征走
Even in international conferences, no one can see her
參加國際會議也沒有人可以看她
that in this meeting
那在這個會議裡面
as soon as she heard
她一聽說
This is a Japanese, so she hit his NDS and took it out
這個是日本人她就打他的 NDS拿出來
All games are in Japanese
所有的game都是日文嘛
I decided to ask this Japanese teacher to help him interpret it.
決定要找這個日本老師來幫他解讀一下
I believe this is also the first time Wada sensei has played in his life
這我相信也是Wada sensei生平第一次玩
Angry Baby Electric Toys
生氣寶貝的電動玩具
It's obviously a lot of fun.
這個有料顯然也很樂在其中
I cherish this photo
那這張照片我自己很珍惜
because it really reflects the
因為這很真實的反映了這個
An attitude towards life as a biologist
光聖物學家他對人生的一個態度
full of everything
對什麼事情都充滿了
positive outlook and enjoyment
正面的看法跟享受
what new things come to him
什麼新的事物來到他身邊
there is a positive energy
就有一個正面的能量
The materials he studies are also very special
他研究的材料也很特殊
Because material is a good cell biologist
因為材料是一個很好的細胞生物學家
Because the material is iron wire
因為材料是鐵線爵
Iron Line Lord is an extinct plant
鐵線爵是一個絕類的植物
It has two levels of four generations
它有兩個層面的四代
One is the fourth generation of double back body
一個是雙背體的四代
One is the three generations of a single back body
一個是單背體的三代
Chromosomes are single and double
就是染色體是單套跟雙套的
Just like we are 46 people
就像我們人是46條
A single set is 23 pieces
單套就是23條
In this single set of four generations
這個單套四代裡面
There is a so-called new type of single-set status
有一個所謂新型的單套的狀況
This single set of lipids
單套細胞脂的這個單套的
Shi Qi
的詩奇
Then this poem is very suitable for some photobiological blood reactions
那這個詩奇呢拿來做一些光生物血的反應非常適合
the reason is because
的原因呢是因為呢
its shape is cute and what
它的形狀很可愛而且呢
It has very few cells
它的細胞的成數很少
Often only one or a few layers of cells
常常只有一到幾層細胞而已
So it is very easy to observe the behavior of some karma bodies under the microscope
所以在顯微鏡下面觀察一些業率體的行為非常的容易
So it is based on the use of this behavior to see
所以說它就在這個利用這個行為來看
Some distributions of these karma
這些業率體的一些分布
Then do some experiments with cellular blood and layered biological blood
然後做一些細胞血跟分層生物血的實驗
Then I'll show you this next
那我接下來給各位看這張
slides also fully reflect it
slides也充分反映出它
An act of pre-call entertainment
預叫娛樂的一個行為
If you still remember when we just watched the movement of chloroplasts
如果說大家還記得我們剛剛看業率體的移動的時候
there is a so-called
就是有所謂的
To approach is to gather and dodge, right?
趨近就是聚集還有躲避的反應對不對
That
那
The next slides is this new shape
下一張slides呢就是這個新狀體
Then it is designed a graphic
那它就是設計了一個圖形
Because this is a unique English is
因為這是一個絕類的英文就是
FIRM
FIRM
It just designed a piece of paper or a
它就是設計了一個紙片啊還是一個
A small one through this transparent light through a membrane
一個小的一個通的這個通透的光通透的一個膜
It says FERN
那上面寫的就是FERN
What passes through the middle of this membrane is weak blue light
那在這個膜的中間所通透的是弱的藍光
So all these karmic bodies have gathered
所以這些業率體都聚集過來了
These other places are also cells one by one.
那其他的這些地方也是一個一個的細胞
But it shines strong blue light
可是它就照很強的藍光
Therefore, these karmic bodies are all avoided to the edge of the cells.
所以說這些業率體就都避到細胞的邊緣去了
So it is natural that it uses such a design
所以說很自然的它就利用這樣子的一個設計
Let a new form in this creature
讓這個生物裡面的一個新狀體
It's an era of unique single-backed bodies
就是一個絕類單背體的時代
renders a word it wants to describe
呈現出它想要描繪的一個字
That is to say, it also praises that the material it studies is a unique one.
就是說也歌頌它研究的這個材料就是一個絕類
This is one that just wasn't highlighted with Photoshop
這是一個就是不是用Photoshop突出來的
is a design through which experiments
是經由它實驗的一個設計
Learn about the karma in the cell with it
跟它了解細胞裡面業率體
or what kind of behavior to move under what circumstances
或在什麼樣的情況下進行什麼樣移動的行為
to finish the design
去設計完
Then design it
然後呢去設計出來
entertaining itself and entertaining people like me
娛樂它自己也娛樂像我這樣子的
Would be very grateful to have an idea like this
非常能夠感激它有這樣子的一個想法
a materialist
的一個資物學家
So this is
所以說這個是
Mr. Wada, he also used this sprouted this
Wada先生他還曾經用這個發芽的這個
This Protonema of one cell of this class
這個絕類的一個細胞的這個Protonema
to change the direction of the blue light
去改變藍光的方向
Because he thinks the blue light is gone
因為他覺得藍光走嘛
He'll let the guy spell his name Wada like this
他就會讓那個拼出他的名字Wada這樣
so very cute scientist
所以是非常可愛的科學家
good
好
So what about the Blu-ray part?
所以藍光的部分呢
I want to give you a brief summary
我想跟大家做一個簡單的總結
so blu ray
所以藍光呢
what we just saw is
我們剛才有看到的就是
Yerity's move
Yerity的移動
When the strong blue light comes
強的藍光來的時候呢
this
這個
Old Big Front Other Siblings
老大牌前面其他的兄弟姊妹
small butcher tag on the back
小的肉牌在後面
so the first one
所以第一個呢
May be exposed to strong blue light
可能會被強烈藍光所受到的
Intense blue light damage
強烈藍光的傷害
There may be free machines in this leaf body
這個葉律體裡面可能產生自由機
moses system or protein in it
它裡面的摩西系統或蛋白質
may take some damage
可能會受到一些傷害
But what about the leaves behind?
可是後面的這些葉律體呢
can be maintained intact
都可以維持完好
but when these
但是當這些
When the blue light comes, it is relatively weak
藍光來的時候是比較弱的時候
or in the cell
或者是說細胞裡面
Two types of people receiving this Blu-ray message
接受這個藍光訊息的兩種
protein or two
蛋白質或兩種
photopixel
像光素
Prototropic OneTwo
Prototropic One跟Two
when damage occurs
產生破壞的時候呢
I can't accept it
我就沒有辦法接受
These strong blue lights come from
這些強的藍光的來
So I'm still scattered in the cytoplasm
所以說我還是依然散佈在細胞質裡面
At this time, for these plants
那這時候對這些植物來講
Is it actually the best way to survive?
事實上是不是生存最適合的方式
So the plant was originally in the wild form
所以說植物原本在野生形裡面
Contains these two proteins
就包含有這兩個蛋白質
Can accept some changes in the environment
可以接受環境裡面逛的一些變化
source of some glare
一些強光的來源
In addition, Nanguang has no chance to introduce to you today.
那另外南廣今天沒有機會跟各位介紹到
related to the opening and closing of stomata
跟氣孔的開合有關
For example, when light comes in, the stomata will open.
比如說光線來氣孔會打開
that light
那光線
It is said that the stomata in the two picture strains
有說在這兩個圖片株裡面的這個氣孔
There is no way to open and close normally
就沒有辦法正常的開合
There's no way to open and close properly. In fact, there are many disadvantages.
那沒有辦法正常開合事實上有很多缺點
for example
比如說
Its gas exchange cannot be normal, right?
它氣體的交換就不能正常對不對
Then the circulation of water and the evaporation of water vapor will also be affected by some transplants
然後水的循環水蒸氣的蒸汕也會受到一些移植
So the water cycle can't be complete
所以說水的循環也沒有辦法完整
what about the other
那另外呢
no chance to tell you
沒有機會跟大家講到
But I think everyone should be able to imagine that
可是我想大家應該也能夠想像的就是
this light
這個光的
The blue light receptor has another so-called silver flower pigment
藍光的受體還有另外一隻所謂的銀花色素
The silver flower pigment is mainly to control the extended seam of this gold
那銀花色素主要是控制這個金的延長餘縫
It is that when it is illuminated, it will not extend so much
就是照光的時候它就比較不會延長那麼多
So in this picture
所以說在這張圖裡面呢
Let me introduce to you
那跟各位介紹就是說
When the light comes from the side in the wild shape
野生形裡面光線從側面來的時候
Its lower fly shaft can be extended and shortened
它的下飛軸延長還可以變短
it can also be photographed
它也可以相光
So it can feel both
所以它可以同時感受兩
Because there are two hands with different blue lights doing different things
因為有兩個不一樣藍光的手體做不一樣的事情
Then what
然後呢
When your camera number is broken
當你相光數壞掉的時候
it has no way of judging the direction
它沒有辦法判斷方向
But it can still feel the shortened matter
可是它縮短的這件事情它還感受得到
so it also knows it doesn't grow too long
所以它還知道它不要長太長
the opposite
那相反的
If you feel the length of the light
如果說你感受到光線長短
You are only suitable when the two extended pigments are broken
你只相配走延長的那兩個引化色素壞掉的時候
This part of its phase light is OK
它相光的這個部分OK
It can still face the direction of the light
它還是可以向著光線的方向
it can feel light
它可以感受到光線
But it has no way to control itself to continue extending
可是它就沒有辦法控制它自己繼續延長
So from this simple diagram it also tells us
所以說從這個簡單的圖示也告訴我們
Plants perceive blue light mainly through two groups of hands
植物感受到藍光主要有兩群藍光的手體
A group is controlling the extension of crystal cloth
一群在控制晶布的延長
a bunch of control
一群在控制
direction of feeling
感受的方向
The direction of the feeling is roughly divided into
那感受的方向大概有分成
The direction the progress moves
進度移動的方向
Also here it is more obvious
還有在這是比較俱觀的
that is more microscopic
那比較微觀的
The direction of movement mentioned by the night traveler inside the cell
在細胞裡面夜旅提的移動方向
Of course some reactions are
想當然有一些反應是
Controlled by blue light and red light
藍光跟紅光共同來調控的
I just want to take a moment to introduce you to
我只要花一點時間跟各位介紹一下
There are several phenomena
有幾個現象是
Plant responses to both red and blue light
植物對紅光跟藍光共同的反應
In this section just now we have looked at many
在這個部分剛才我們已經看很多
by
是藉由
Pigment control of luciferin and blue light absorption
光明素跟藍光的吸收的色素控制
extension of lower peto
下佩陀的延長
Next we spend most of our time
接下來我們把大部分的時間
are placed in common with the other two
都放在另外兩個共同
Plant responses controlled by blue and red light
由藍光跟紅光控制植物的反應
is the establishment of the biological clock
就是生物時鐘的建立
control of flowering time
還有開花時間的調控
So let's talk about the difference between blue light and red light
所以要講到藍光跟紅光之間
common regulation or biological clock
共同的調控或生物時鐘
Let's start with a
我們先講到一個
One phenomenon is the so-called photoperiod
一個現象就是所謂的光周期
It's not about school
這並不是在講學校裡面
or in the Academia Sinica
或是中央研究院裡面的
teacher you will bring students stories
老師你會帶學生的故事
So it's talking
所以說這是在講
The main thing to look at is these two plants
主要看的是這兩顆植物
Then this is just the indicator of the doll
那這個只是人形的這個指標
How big is this plant
這個植物到底是長多大
But judging from this age, it is indeed possible that the relationship between illegitimate children is abusive to each other, and it is also possible
但是從這個年齡來看的確有可能是私生之間的互相虐待關係也是有可能
This is a normal tobacco plant
這個是一個正常的菸草植物
it blooms in summer
它在夏天的時候會開花
It's already on the top, I've already bloomed here, so I can't see clearly
這裡已經在頂部,我這裡已經開花,就看不清楚
it's blooming
這裡已經開花了
This is a mutant
這是一個突變株
It replaces a sensor time, a gene that senses daily
它換掉了一個感應時間,感應日常的一個基因
After replacing it, it just grows leaves and doesn't bloom
換掉了之後,它就光長葉子,不開花
The cycle of plant growth is mainly divided into vegetative period and reproductive period
對植物生長的周期來講,主要分成成營養時期和生殖時期
The vegetative period is when the leaves grow
營養時期就是長葉子
When the environment is right, all the conditions are ripe
長到環境對了,所有一切的條件都成熟了
Then I want to enter the reproductive period, and then I can start to enter the flowering period
那我要進入生殖時期,就可以開始進入開花的時期
This tobacco, it just has a young shape, and there is no way to enter the reproductive period
這顆菸草,它就是有一顆年輕的形,沒有辦法進入生殖時期
So in the timing environment the same happens for both grows
所以在計時環境對這兩個生長的情況一樣
As you can see, this one has reached the roof of the greenhouse and it's still light with long leaves
你可以看到,這個都已經到溫室的屋頂,它還是光長葉子
So it leads to another question
所以就衍生到另外一個問題
Well, how do my plants know?
好那我植物怎麼知道
Time is up
時間到了
how do you know right now
怎麼知道現在對
In general, plants can be distinguished
一般來講植物可以區分
Not every plant will
不是每種植物都會
In line with the two I will talk about below
符合我以下要講的這兩個
form
形態
The first is the so-called short-day plants
第一個就是所謂的短日照植物
short day plants
短日照植物的意思
by this name
以這個名字來看
it wishes the days were a little shorter
它希望白天的時間稍微短一點
it will bloom
它才會開花
For example, in early spring
比如說在早春的時候
or winter
或是冬天
or in autumn
或是生秋的時候
Sunshine duration comparison short
日照時間比較短
it will bloom
它會開花
Assuming this is 24 hours a day
假設這個是一天24小時
That is, we run in Dazhi Station
就是我們在大直站裡面運行
is a day 24 hours
一天是24小時嘛
if we still
如果說我們還是
while the sun is turning
在太陽在轉頭
our day is 24 hours
我們一天是24小時
24 hours a day
那一天24小時
So you can see this yellow is the day part
所以你可以看到這個黃色是白天的部分
gray is the night part
灰色是晚上的部分
so when your daylight hours
所以當你的日照時間
longer than night time
長於晚上時間的時候
this plant does not bloom
這個植物就不開花
or your daylight hours
或者是說你的日照時間
shorter than night time
比晚上時間短的時候
under the condition of so-called short daylight
就是所謂短日照的情況之下
this plant blooms
這個植物就開花
Of course I want to say
那當然就會想說
So am I two days or two nights?
那我到底是兩白天還是兩晚上
right
對不對
so i can do an experiment
所以我可以學家做一個實驗
He just makes the night a flash of light
他就是把晚上做一個光的閃光
maybe a few minutes of flash
可能是幾分鐘的閃光
Then I mess up the schedule for the evening.
那我就打亂了這個晚上的時程
Because the days are still as short
因為白天還是一樣短
But this time the plants are not blooming
可是這個時候植物不開花
So if we say to do this experiment
所以說如果說做這個實驗
let you guys decide
那讓各位來決定說
How do plants feel the length of the day?
那植物到底是感受白天的長度
or the length of the night
還是晚上的長度
what do you think it is feeling
你會覺得它是感受什麼
night
晚上
oh good
喔很好
Hey, everyone who is interested in coming to my laboratory
欸那個各位有興趣要來我實驗室
What has been done in botanical research
進行植物學研究過什麼
Because the reaction is too fast
因為實在是反應太迅速
So this is
所以說這是
The length of time a night is detected
偵測到一個晚上的時間的長度
So in fact it is like
所以事實上它是喜歡
How long are the two nights
側兩晚上的時間有多長
to have a continuous
要有一個連續的
length of night
晚上的長度
That opposite long-day plant is like
那相反的長日照植物就是喜歡
longer days
白天比較長
that or the night is shorter
那或者是晚上比較短
so look at this picture
所以你看這個圖語
In fact, it also fits this play
事實上也符合這個玩段
That is, long-day plants have very long days.
就是長日照植物白天很長
bloom that night
當晚開花
daytime hours below a transit point
白天時間低於一個凌接點
it doesn't bloom
它不開花
If you say that you shine a little longer at night
如果說你晚上照光的時間稍微再長一點
When it breaks the length of its continuous night
破壞掉它這個連續的晚上的長度的時候
It will also think it seems like it has enough sun time
它也會認為它好像有足夠的太陽的時間
it will bloom too
它也會開花
This is a fresh plant
這常鮮造植物
Many plants will be classified in both
很多植物都會歸類在這兩者
Some plants are less sensitive to the length of the day
有些植物就是對日照的長度比較不敏感
So the plant called heavy Dayneutral
所以叫做重性的 Dayneutral 的植物
There are also some so-called firmly believed fresh artificial plants
也有一些是所謂的堅信常鮮造植物
That's when it likes to make it fresh
就是它喜歡在常鮮造的時間的時候
bloom earlier
早一點開花
But if you insist on growing it in short-day conditions
但是如果你硬要讓它生長在短日照的情況之下
After a long time, it will bloom as a last resort
久了它也不得已也會開花
Are there different types of plants?
是不是植物有各式各樣不同的種類
However, conceptually it can be divided into two
但是主要以概念上來講可以分成這兩種
So this is another example
所以說這是另外一個例子
Am I measuring the length of the day or the length of the night?
我到底是測量日長還是測量夜長
So it's twenty-four hours a day
所以說這是一天二十四小時
This is a short day plant
這是一個短日照的植物
So the days are shorter
所以說白天比較短
It blooms when the night is longer
晚上比較長的時候它開花
The days are longer and the nights are shorter
白天比較長 晚上比較短 不行
It looks like daytime when it's illuminated at night
晚上照光了之後看起來也是白天
It's a long day and it doesn't bloom
那天比較長 不開花
Then this Wenpi scientist is about to appear.
那這個 文皮的科學家要出現了
Then I'll adjust the two as well
那我把它兩個調一樣好了
Just not 20 hours a day
就是一天不要20小時
I adjust a growth phase to let it inside
我調一個生長相讓它裡面
18 hours a day or 16 hours
一天是18個小時 或是16個小時
Both are the same length, no
兩個一樣長 不行
Then my days and nights are also very long
那我白天晚上也很長好了
OK, there will be flowers here.
好 可以 這就有開花
So here's another example to show us
所以這是另外一個例子來告訴我們
it measures the time of night
它測量的是晚上的時間
good
好
Then I'll just measure the time
那 我就 只要測量這個時間
how does it know where this time is
它怎麼知道這個時間在哪裡
if you remember
如果大家還記得的話
or how do i know
或是說我怎麼知道
I've been in the sun for a few days
我已經幾天白天照多久的太陽了
that's how I count
就是我怎麼算
how do i calculate how long a day is
我怎麼算一天多長
How long is the day and how long is the night
一天白天多長 晚上多長
i can see light
我能夠看到光
just let everyone understand
就讓大家可以理解
see it
看到就看到了嘛
But when we have to measure this time again
但是還要再測量這個時間的時候
That sounds a little difficult, doesn't it?
這聽起來就有點困難對不對
So if you remember this
所以如果大家還記得這個
we just watched wrist beans
我們剛剛看了腕豆
normal carpus it blooms
正常的腕豆它會開花
Brachiopsis lacks brightin
腕豆缺少了光明素
When the pigment body that absorbs the red light source, the red light
吸收紅光源 紅光的那個色素體的時候
it won't bloom
它就不開華了
so say say
所以說表示說
There is no way to measure the temperature in this case
溫度在這個情況下沒有辦法測量
some changes along the way
走齊的一些變化
no way to measure
沒有辦法測量
a signal from the light
光線給它的一個訊號
Then we will talk about it
那這時候就要講到
when the light comes in
光線進來的時候
In fact, light and temperature will also
光線其實跟溫度也會
Both light and temperature will make plants
光線跟溫度都會讓植物
In fact, people are too
能夠其實人也是了
Can feel the changes in the current environment
能夠感受到現在環境裡面的變化
how long is the day now
現在白天是多長
how long is the night
晚上是多長
24 hours a day tour changes
一天24小時的巡迴的變化
that can also train plants
那也可以訓練植物
to build a living organism inside a cell always
去建立一個細胞裡面的生物始終
then we can
那我們可以
sorry for that plant
那植物對不起
I imagine myself as the Arab world
我把我自己想像成阿拉伯界
make plants predictable
讓植物可以預期
tomorrow morning
明天早上
When is 6 o'clock and 8 o'clock?
6點鐘跟8點鐘是什麼時候來
That is a built-in creature always
那就是一個內建的生物始終
I have a habit every day
我每天有一個習慣
what time do i want to do
我要在什麼時間要去做什麼事情
So the creature always has three main
所以這生物始終有三個主要的
elements of operation
運作的元素
The first one must have light come in
第一個就必須要有光進來
Passage of photons
經過光壽體
For example, the bright element we just talked about
比如說我們剛剛講的光明素
or luciferase
或者是螢化色素
after receiving
接收之後
new signal
新來的訊號
to help build up the missing organisms inside the cells
就幫助細胞裡面的生物失蹤的建立
It is called a Central Oscillator
就是所謂一個 Central Oscillator
build heat creature missing
建立熱生物失蹤
after operation
在運作之後
The creature is missing as soon as it starts functioning it can be measured
生物失蹤一開始運作它就可以測量
how much daylight is every day
每天的白天是多少
how much is the night
晚上是多少
After that established
那建立了之後
it can then tell some of its downstream physiological responses that
它就可以告訴它下游的一些生理反應說
ok you can flower now
好啦 你現在可以開花啦
You can now open the air control
你現在氣控可以打開啦
You can now do some op-filtering, growing, etc.
你現在可以做一些運濾的生長等等
The growth of these transport filters
那這些運濾的生長
Let's look at some examples
我們可以來看一些例子
Where is the creature missing?
那生物失蹤呢
This was in a joint newspaper last year
這個在去年的一個聯合報
I want these below the road
我想在路以下的這些
It may be more relevant to you
可能跟各位比較有確身相關
There are animals and there are things that are missing
生物失蹤之物有動物也有
What about the missing animal creature?
那動物的生物失蹤呢
can be explained at different times
就可以解釋在不一樣的時間
like midnight
比如說半夜的時候
you may start to sleep
你可能開始想睡覺啦
slow gastrointestinal motility
腸胃滷動變慢
Then it might be easier to have
那這時候可能也比較容易有
dangerous diseases
危險性的一些疾病的產生
What are some physiological and biochemical reactions?
還有一些生理生化的反應是什麼等等
This is more related to the disappearance of creatures compared to people
這是跟人比較生物失蹤比較相關
The plants are the same to people as they are to people.
那植物對人跟人相同也是
Of course there may not be some stroke
當然可能不會有些腦中風
We just talked about some diseases
我們剛剛講到一些疾病
But there will also be some missing creatures
但是也會有一些生物失蹤的產生
What about the life clock? Its English name is Sacadian with him
生活時鐘呢 它的英文叫作Sacadian with him
That's the meaning of the law
那這個是結律的意思
life clock
生活時鐘又叫概約韻律
Sacadian is a Latin prefix
Sacadian 這個是一個拉丁文的字首
It is Sacadian, which means about a day
就是Sacadian 就是大約是一天的意思
So a 24 hour cycle
所以說一天24小時的循環
There are many cycles in nature that are not 24 hours
那自然界裡面有很多循環不是24小時
For example, tides are not
比如說潮汐就不是
Then there are some loops
那也有一些就是循環
as long as it's a cycle it's a cycle
只要是一個循環就是一個循環
The length of time is not certain
那時間的長短不一定
But if say with
但是如果說搭配著
The Ninth Rotation and Part of the Ninth Rotation
第九自轉跟第九自轉的部分
If facing the sun, a day is 24 hours
對著太陽的話就一天是24小時
Life clocks are very widespread in a wide variety of organisms
生活時鐘非常廣泛存在各式各樣的生物裡面
From the simplest blue-green palm
從最簡單的藍綠掌
unicellular blue-green palm
單細胞的藍綠掌
to higher fungi
到比較高等的真菌類
For example, Negotiper to the animal kingdom, the plant kingdom
比如說Negotiper 到動物界 植物界
Many creatures have found the presence of missing inner creatures
很多的生物都發現有內在生物失蹤的存在
What does the plant's biology go missing?
那植物的生物失蹤管什麼
manage a lot
管很多
Life Clock tubes some elite performances
生活時鐘管一些精英的表現
Some genes are expressed more in the morning and less in the evening
一些基因的表現都是早上比較多 晚上比較少
Or some plans are more and less in the morning
或者一些方案比較多 早上比較少
Changes in the concentration of some ions in the tube cells
那管細胞裡面一些離子的濃度的變化
Regardless of whether some proteins have to undergo specialization
管一些蛋白質是不是要經過特殊的特化
Or the opening of the mobile air hole led by the pipe industry
或是管業率體的移動氣孔的打開
or like going at an extended speed
或者像會走的延長的速度
You look at the mass over there as if it's all the same rate
你要看質量在那邊長好像它都是一樣的速率
It actually grows fastest in the early morning
它事實上在清晨的時候長到最快
So at the dawn of each day
所以在每天破曉的時候
It will only grow, progress and extend the fastest
只會長 進步延長的最快
or some career moves
或者是職業的一些移動
Wait a minute and you will have a chance to see a short video
等一下各位會有機會看到一段小影片
The opening and closing of the flowers, of course, the Qianliuhua we saw at the beginning
那花的開合 當然我們最開始的時候看到的那個千流花
its opening and closing
它的開合
and control of flowering time, etc.
以及開花時間的控制等等
These are all biological clocks
這些都是生物時鐘來管俠
Then I think the most familiar example is
那我想大家最熟知的例子就是
Sunflowers will face the sun, right?
向日葵會向日對不對
That
那
This is a sunflower plant
這是一個向日葵的植物
It's actually a young sunflower
它事實上這是一個年輕的向日葵
This is a sunflower leaf
這是向日葵的葉片
this side is east this side is west side
這邊是東邊 這邊是西邊
So in the morning after the sun comes in at noon
所以早上太陽進來之後在正中午的時候
The leaves of the sunflower
這個向日葵的葉片
Expand like a sun and start photosynthesis, etc.
展開像個太陽開始進行光合作用等等
Of course the time passed in the afternoon
當然時間往下午過去呢
he starts facing west
他開始面向西邊
Facing a west sunset
面向是個西邊日落
then when night comes
然後晚上到來的時候
The whole night begins to blow
整個夜片開始下吹
that's amazing
那很神奇的喔
Wait a minute and the sun will come out when you see this thing, right?
你等一下看到這東西都太陽要出來對不對
when the sun can still come out
太陽還能出來的時候
You see his leaves are already
你看他的葉子都已經
Ready
準備好了
good
好
he knows
他知道
He knows where the sun is going to come out
他知道太陽要從哪裡出來了
he also wants to get ready
他也要get ready
he has to be ready
他也要準備好
The sun comes out and live there small
太陽出來在那邊活小的
build like a clock
像個時鐘的建立
Allowing organisms to anticipate future changes in the environment
讓生物可以預期環境未來的變化
as long as it changes periodically
只要他是週期變化的
I can go through the establishment of biological clock
我就可以經過生物時鐘的建立
tell the director
告訴主任
when do you get ready early
什麼時候你要提早準備好
I should be able to use this example
我應該可以用這個例子
to tell my daughter about her test preparation
來告訴我女兒準備考試的事情
then this is
那這個就是
Another common misconception we have
另外一個我們常常有的誤解
that is to say like a sunflower
就是說像日葵
That means he should be chasing the sun, right?
就是說他應該會追著太陽對不對
but i think
可是我想
Everyone should be able to imagine
應該大家也可以想像
If living things can grow well
如果生物可以長好了之後
that head is so heavy
那個頭那麼重
Why is there still a way to turn left at all?
怎麼還有辦法一點都往左來轉
So this is too difficult for it
所以說這個是也太為難它了
So in fact like the leaves of a sunflower
所以事實上像日葵的葉片
The phenomenon of chasing the sun will exist
追日的現象會存在
i am young plants especially obvious
我是年輕的植物特別的明顯
But mature like this flower of a sunflower
但是成熟的像日葵的這個花朵
the part that produces the sunflower seeds
就產生葵花子的這個部分
it will of course go west
它當然會向西邊
good
好
that except the leaves follow the sun
那除了葉片追隨著太陽
In addition, the life clock also controls the movement of many plants.
那另外生活時鐘還控制了很多植物的運動
for example
比如說
in this is a
在這個是一個
But the leaves of planted plants will follow
但是受植業植物它的葉片會隨著
The swing of the blades is carried out at different times of the day
每天不同的時間再進行葉片的擺動
Maybe that angle at night is the same as this angle
可能晚上的時候那個角度跟這個角度
Clamp feet are relatively small
夾腳比較小
Open to receive sunlight during the day
白天的時候就打開接收陽光
It will hang down at night
那晚上的時候就會垂下來
that life clock
那生活時鐘
How does it work when you're in the west
當你在西方裡面怎麼運作
I have a few slides to briefly explain to you
我有幾張slides跟大家簡單說明一下
So the living clock has three elements
所以生活時鐘有三個要件
The first requirement is to have a government
第一個要件就是要有一個政府
That is to say when the life clock is at its highest
就是說生活時鐘什麼時候要最高
when is the lowest
什麼時候最低
What is the difference between high and low
高跟低之間的差距是多少
is the whole
就是整個
what is the difference
差別是多少
Some creatures are already slow
有的生物已經很緩
because of the large
因為生物之中很大
The second is to say
第二個就是說
where is my highest point
我起來最高點在哪裡
or where is the lowest point
或是最低點在哪裡
Where is the relative position
相對位置在哪裡
This is the so-called face
這是所謂的face
The other is the length of a cycle
另外一個就是一個週期的長度是多少
For most living things on earth
對於大部分地球上的生物來講
almost 24 hours
都差不多是24小時
Because long-term evolution follows our environment
因為長久的演化跟隨著我們環境
always in sync
一直同步
so almost 24 hours
所以差不多是24個小時
But following biological
但是跟隨著生物來講
its time is not quite the same
它的時間其實不大相同
sometimes a little longer
有的時候稍微長一點點
also slightly shorter
也是稍微短一點點
So this is three elements
所以這個是三個要件
we were just talking
我們剛剛在講說
This figure has three elements
這個圖有三個要件
when among living things
就是生物之中的時候
often draw this waveform
常常畫出這個波形
like a birth mother
就好像是生婆
or the spring lady
或者是彈簧婆
there will be some waveforms
就會有一些波形
How are these waveforms generated
這些波形是怎麼產生的
I must have this waveform
我一定要有這個波形
i just know
我才知道說
how it works in my biology
我生物之中是怎麼運作
where is my vertex
我的頂點在哪裡
where is my low point
我的低點在哪裡
If the horizontal axis is time
如果橫軸是時間的話
I will know my apex
我才會知道我這個頂點
or what time
或是哪一個時間的來
Therefore, some digital measurements are often required so that biological plasma can produce this waveform
所以說常常就需要一些數字化的測量讓生物血漿可以製造出這個波形
Then give it some meaning and common sense to explain some biological phenomena that can be explained behind it
然後來賦予它一些意義跟常識解釋它背後所能夠解釋的一些生物的現象
For example, here is the figure we just talked about where the blade can swing up and down
比如說現在這裡就是我們剛剛講的一個葉片可以上下擺動的那個圖形
We can make an angle between it and the horizontal and measure that angle
我們就可以把它跟水平的地方做一個夾角就會測量那個角度
At different times, there is a different angle with the horizontal
在不同的時間裡面就跟水平有一個不同的夾角
Measure different 24-hour period measurements 1, 2, 3, 4, 5
測量不同的24小時的週期測量1、2、3、4、5
After measuring 6 or 7 cycles, we can see the generation of this waveform
測量6、7個週期之後我們就可以看到這個波形的產生
So say this is a way
所以說這是一種方法
You can measure some physiological responses such as the angle between the leaf and the horizontal
你可以測量一些生理的反應比如說葉子跟水平的一個夾角
Or you can measure gene expression
或者你也可以測量基因的表現
Many of them are now talking about all the physiological reaction phenomena and so on.
很多現在就是講到一些所有的生理的反應現象等等
It's actually a result of genetic expression
事實上都是基因表現的一個結果
So if we want to study the performance of a gene
所以說如果我們要研究一個基因的表現
The main structure of a gene is that it has a start value that is responsible for
基因主要的結構就是它有一個啟動值就是負責
activate the expression of this gene
啟動這個基因的表現
This startup value often has many single values to regulate
這個啟動值常常會有很多單本值來調控
He come tell him you do this you do that
他來告訴他你要做這個你要做那個
How much do you show now
你現在要表現你要表現多少
or you don't act now
或是你現在不要表現
So the behavior of this startup value itself
所以這個啟動值本身的行為
It represents the possible behavior of this gene in the cell
就代表了這個基因可能在細胞裡面表現的行為
But
可是
I can't see him there, can I?
他在那裡我沒有看不到對不對
So often one of the things biologists do
所以常常生物學家會做的一件事情
is followed by a reporter gene
就是在後面接上一個報導基因
We will know the nature of this reporter gene
這個報導基因我們會知道他的性質是什麼
we will know what food he likes to eat
我們會知道他喜歡吃什麼食物
After eating something, he will spit out a product
吃了什麼食物之後他就會吐出一個產物
That product may emit some biological luminescence
那個產物可能會發出一些生物的冷光
As long as there is light, we can do detection
只要會發光的我們就可以做偵測
For example, adding a starting value to this particle
比如說像這個粒子裡面加上啟動值
Let's catch a cold light
我們就接上一個冷光
he will be in a special
他就會在一個特殊的
Luminous
冷光的
under the camera he can see
照相機下面他就可以看到
This value emits light
這個值會發出光線
So you can imagine this gene
所以你可以想像出這個基因
All of a sudden, all of a sudden, all of a sudden, all of a sudden, all of a sudden
一下子有一下子沒有一下子有一下沒有
Then you are under this camera and you take pictures in the way we just told the truth
那你在這個照相機下面你用我們剛才那個說實攝影的方式去拍照
Can you see it turn on and off
你是不是可以看到一下亮一下不亮
can imagine
可以想像
let's take a look
我們來看一下
this is
這個就是
Wait a minute and you'll see a row of plants
等一下你會看到一排植物
It just has two leaves and two small
它就是有兩個植葉跟有兩個小的
coniferous
針葉
Then use the method of time-lapse projection to see the results of this reporter gene expression
那用縮時射影的方式去看看這個報導基因表現的結果
So this is a plant from the Arab world
所以這是阿拉伯界的植株
These two plant leaves These two are needles
這兩個植葉 這兩個是針葉
So this is after three or four days of continuous shooting
所以這個是連續拍攝了三四天之後呢
exist
在
fast and fast
以快速不放的方式
to tell everyone
來告訴大家
can be used in such a way
可以利用這樣子的方式
So you can base
所以說你就可以根據
this is a lot of images
這是很多個影像
get together
聚集起來
You will do quantification based on different images
你會根據不同的影像去做定量
you can make this waveform
你就可以做出這個波形
this is also a study
這也是一個研究
A frequently used tool for gene expression regulated by biological prey
受生物食衆所調控基因表現的一個常常利用到的工具
There is another characteristic of biological eaters, that is,
生物食衆還有一個特性就是說
After it is trained
它被訓練完之後呢
it can be done in the same way
它可以以同樣的方式
Even if you don't train it anymore
就算你不再訓練它了
You remove the factor of environmental constraints
你把這個環境制約的因素拿掉
For example
比如說呢
After a week of training I started giving him 12 hours of day and dark
我一開始給它白天黑暗的各12個小時訓練的一個禮拜之後
Bioeater builds strong
生物食衆建立得很強壯
At this time suddenly funded it
這時候突然資給它
The light environment does not give it darkness
光照的環境不給它黑暗
Or give it a dark environment without giving it light
或是資給它黑暗的環境不給它光照
My biological eater will continue
我這個生物食衆還會繼續持續
But the government will slowly get a little bit smaller
但是政府會慢慢稍微變小一點
Then I think this has something to do with everyone.
那這個我想跟大家切身比較有關係
For example, flying to a country with a different urban area
比如說飛到一個不一樣的市區的國家
There will be some parallax at first
開始會有一些視差
It's also because we were trained in Taiwan
這也是因為我們在台灣被訓練好了
We are used to this time being morning and evening
我們就是習慣這個時間是早上跟晚上
When you're dropped into a different urban area
當你被放到一個不一樣的市區的時候
You still keep your inner bioeater going
你依然維持你內在的生物食衆的運作
Well, the genes of that profession know what time it is.
好 那職業的基因會知道現在是幾點鐘
For example in this example
比如說在這個例子
We're pretty used to seeing this waveform by now.
我們現在已經很習慣看這個波形了
Then this waveform has two colors
那這個波形有兩個顏色
One that is red is the gene expressed in the morning
一個是紅色就是早上所表現的基因
it's morning it's morning
就是早上這個是早上
there are some evening genes
那有一些是傍晚的基因
especially high in the evening
傍晚表現得特別高
when we had that design just now
當我們剛才有那個設計的時候
You'll find out which genes are more abundant in the morning
你會找出哪些基因是早上特別多
Which genes are more abundant at night
哪些基因是晚上特別多
Then why have these two
那為什麼要有這兩種
There are morning genes and evening genes
有早上的基因跟晚上的基因
In fact, it allows organisms to build
事實上是讓生物能夠建立
Biology always has a very important foundation
生物始終有一個非常重要的基礎
the reason is this
原因是這樣
For example
比如說呢
this is night
這個是晚上
this is daytime
這個是白天
What about after I have the morning genes?
那我有早上的基因出來之後呢
it's these two
是這兩個
what about these two
那這兩個呢
He just can't see others well
他就是看不得別人好
when i become more
我變多的時候呢
I'm going to suppress the emergence of the evening gene
我就要抑制傍晚的基因的出現
So I just load
所以我只要載
I just load during the day
我白天只要載
I am
我就是
dominate
主宰
I don't let the evening genes show up
我不讓傍晚的基因出現
Until the activation value of my gene started to weaken
一直到我這個基因的啟動值開始變弱了
My gene expression is going to be less
我這個基因的表現要變少了
I was able to lose my will to him
我才能夠失去對他的意志
at this time in this
這時候在這個
Authoritarian evening genes finally able to perform
威權下的傍晚的基因終於能夠表現
but he
可是他
No
沒有
not likely to retaliate
不大會報復
He will actually help find the genetic expression
他事實上會幫助找成的基因表現
So after he helped find the genetic expression
所以他幫助找成的基因表現之後
came back to realize his own performance
又回過來意識他自己的表現
so what
所以呢
This is a kind that is often seen in biology
這是在生物始終裡面常常看到的一種
So-called
所謂的
negative feedback control
負向回饋控制
that is
就是
one up
一個上來
awareness of another
意識另外一個
Until he can't realize it
一直到他沒有辦法意識到的時候
another up
另外一個起來了
What about when the other one wakes up?
那另外一個起來之後呢
He showed another
他又出示另外一個
Therefore, a cycle of 24 hours a day is established between positive and negative
所以一正一反之間就建立了一天24小時的循環
So the creature is missing inside
所以說生物失蹤裡面
Simple one basic molecular mechanism
簡單的一個基本的分子機制
Such molecular mechanisms are expected to exist in a wide variety of biological systems
這樣的分子機制是向廣泛存在各式各樣的生物系統裡面
For example, in rats, in state-owned plants, in Arab-built plants
比如說在老鼠、在國營、在阿拉伯建植物裡面
Both have the so-called one positive and one negative loop structure
都有所謂一正一反的迴圈的構造
This loop may only have one loop or two loops or five loops
這個迴圈可能只有一個迴圈或兩個迴圈或五個迴圈
or even more loops
或甚至更多的迴圈
The ingredients in it are not quite the same
它裡面的組成成分沒有非常的相同
But the concepts used are very similar
但是用到的概念都非常的類似
Also for your reference
也給各位做參考
ok i think last
好,我想最後呢
I don't think it's too early
我想時間也不早
I want to use two photos to summarize with everyone
我想用兩張是來跟大家summarize
This is the part I will introduce to you today
這是我今天跟各位介紹的部分
It is how to see the light environment afterwards
就是之后怎麼樣看見光的環境
The light environment has UV
光的環境有UV
Up to blue light, red light and round red light in visible light
一直到可見光裡面的藍光、紅光跟圓紅光
different pigments after
之后有不同的色素
Some brightness and qualities of these lights are acceptable
可以接受到這些光的一些亮跟品質
What kind of light is coming in now, what kind of abnormal light is in the environment
現在進來的是什麼光,環境裡面是有什麼樣破常的光
What is the ratio of each other
彼此之間的比例是多少
If I have these pigments receiving these rays
我如果有這些色素在接受這些光線
Then I also tell others how much I have received now, let's compare
然後我也告訴別人說我現在受到多少,來我們來比較一下
Then compare the results and synthesize them, so that plants can interpret
那比較這個結果就綜合了,讓植物可以解讀
What is the external light environment now, and what kind of response should be done
現在外在的光環境是什麼,應該做什麼樣的反應
What about these reactions, from the implantation of front teeth to the growth of small seedlings
那這些反應呢,就包括從種植門牙到小幼苗的生長
To avoid phagocytosis, to the movement of something like light or liquid in cells
到躲避噬陰,到一些像光或者細胞裡面液律體的移動
to the process of final flowering or the establishment of biological anaxia, etc.
到最後開花的過程或生物失動的建立等等
These are all because there are some light receptors in the plant
這些都是因為植物裡面有一些光的受體
After a series of biological reactions, it tells the plant
它在經過一連串的生物反應之後,告訴植物
Can make the most appropriate adjustments to the light environment in which we live now
針對現在所生存的光的環境能夠做出最適切的調整
with growth and development
跟生長,還有發育
In the end, use this slice with
那最後呢,用這張slice跟
Thank you all for taking so long to sit here today
謝謝大家今天花這麼長的時間坐在這裡
It also gave me the opportunity to help with research topics that I am very passionate about.
也讓我有機會幫我自己非常熱愛的研究的課題
have the opportunity to share with you
能夠有機會跟大家分享
that in nature i think
那在自然界裡面我想
Everywhere, especially in the face of plants, there are often
處處,尤其是面對植物常常會有
Lots of surprises and beautiful pictures
非常多的驚喜跟非常美麗的畫面
I also hope that you will spend so long here tonight
也希望各位在今天晚上花這麼長的時間在這裡
I can also be safe with my family
能夠也和家平安
what's the problem if wait
如果等一下有什麼問題
I am also very proud to have further discussions with you
我也很得意跟大家做進一步的討論
thank you
謝謝各位
Thank you Dr. Wu for introducing the world of plants
謝謝吳博士介紹的植物的世界
with its life affected by light
跟它受光的影響的一生
then we are open to ask questions
那我們開放問問題的話
good
好
press the green
按那個綠色的
ok, teacher wu, may i ask
ok 吳老師請問一下
different vegetables
不同的蔬菜
Let's talk about how different vegetable groups respond to light
我們講不同的蔬菜的科別對於光的反應
For example, the wavelength of the response of blue light
比如說藍光的反應的波長
Or will the wavelength of red light be the same?
或是紅光的波長會一樣嗎
I guess again
我再猜啦
that is to say it could be very close
就是說可能會非常的接近
Then this may decide, if you remember that we had a spectrum of Xiguang just now
那這個可能會決定,如果說您還記得剛才我們有一個西光的光譜的話
You will find that its newly received wavelength actually has a certain range
你會發現它新收的波長事實上也有一定的範圍
It's not that only at 400 or 380
它也不是說只有在400或380
it's probably around 350 to 420
它可能是在350到420左右
So maybe look inside the species of this plant you are interested in
所以可能看您有興趣的這個植物的種類裡面
What is the structure of its light receptor
它的光的受體的結構是什麼
So but I'm sure it's probably not like
所以說但是我相信大概不會是比如說
Does not jump from 350 to 450
不會從350跳成450
Of course it will be in that mission
當然會是在那個任務裡面
Maybe the pick at the tip will be a little bit shifted left and right
也許在最尖端的pick會有點左右偏移而已
So different ones should be the same
所以不同顆應該會一樣
My idea is to say
我的想法是說
like olives and kegs
比如說橄欖菜跟小桶號
then we can control its different wavelengths
那我們可以控制它不同的波長
Can control its different growth rate
可以控制它不同的生長的速度
It might work
應該可以吧
Yes, in fact there are some
對,事實上是有一些
I know there are some people who think of growing as cultivating
我了解有一些做生長想就是栽培式的人
He'll actually add some different shades of light to encourage plant growth
他會事實上會補一些不同的色光來促進植物的生長
For example, add some red light or some blue light
比如說補一些紅光或補一些藍光
Indeed there is such a situation
的確是有這樣的狀況
Thank you, Mr. Wu, you are wonderful and clear
吳老師謝謝你很精彩很清楚
You just mentioned that the light is stronger and there is an avoidance reaction
你剛有談到就是光比較強有一個躲避的反應
Our side is especially in the Yale belt or when the summer sun is in the middle of the tropics
我們這邊特別雅樂帶或熱帶地區夏天日正當中的時候
The sun is very strong, the UV index is even harmful to people
陽光很強,UV指數甚至人對人都有害
So I'm wondering is dodging enough? Do they have
所以我在想光躲避夠嗎?他們是不是有
Can you not talk about other mechanisms? If
可以不會談到還有其他的機制?如果
If the light is too strong or its energy is too strong
光亮太強或他能量太強的話
Is there any kind?
有沒有什麼樣的?
Because lawyer Ye in the row in front has been dying until the flames
因為前面一排葉律師一直死到烘焰去
More may not sacrifice enough
更多可能也犧牲不夠
i think what do you mean
我想你的意思是怎樣
Yes, plants actually have some other mechanism
有的,植物事實上有一些其他的機制
For example, on high mountains you can see a lot of leaves
比如說在高山上你可以看到很多的葉片
it has a lot of melt hair on it
它上面有很多熔毛
hairy on the leaves
就葉片上毛毛的
It's actually a specialized tissue of the epidermis
它事實上是一個表皮的特化組織
The melting hairs are different because of their different angles.
那這些熔毛因為它長的角度不一樣
So it can be refracted by UV
所以說UV來它會可以折射
so it can be lower
所以它可以降低一些
These high energies come in and make the temperature of the plant bigger
這些高的能量進來讓植物的溫度變大
Too high, or generate too much energy, generate a lot of free machines
太高啦 或產生很多的能量太多 產生很多自由機
So it's a kind of
所以這是一種
that or he will
那或者是他會
For example, if the plants are really, you will see some drooping
比如說植物真的 你會看到有些下垂的
As soon as the leaves start drooping, he won't follow
就葉片開始會往下垂 那他就不會跟
The light comes from the feet
光線來的是指腳
That is to say, he lowered the area of acceptance a little.
就是說他降低一點接受的面積
that or
那或者是說
If the trachea is opened wide, it is easy for him to be under such high temperature
如果說氣管打得很開 他很容易在這麼高溫下面
he keeps evaporating
他一直蒸散
His plants will be short of water and will have tail vultures
他植物就會缺水就會尾雕
So he might have some conditions where he'll shut off the windpipe.
所以他可能有些狀況之下 他會把氣管關起來
Keep plants from comparing
讓植物不會在比較
In an environment without dispersal, it is easy to lack water
不有散的環境時下滿容易缺水
So plants are actually colorful and interesting
所以說植物其實顏色植物滿有趣
It's because people can build energy chambers
就是因為人可以健能氣房嘛
That plant is there, he just has to withstand the wind, vertically bask in the rain
那植物就在那裡 他就是要忍收風 垂直曬雨大
What about today, the weather will be better, and tomorrow the weather will be worse
那今天呢 天氣好一點 明天天氣不好一點
he has to endure
他都要忍收
So he has all sorts of mechanics
所以他有各式各樣的機制
You can let him be a little tougher
可以去讓他自己能夠Tough一點
Be able to accept the environment a little more
能夠認收環境多一點
inside you mean for example
體內 你是說比如說
You said molecular level
你說分子的層次啊
Because you just said that he has a free machine
因為你剛才講說他有產生自由機
we know this
我們知道這個
So it also has some mechanisms for removing free machines
所以它也有一些去除自由機的一些機制
Or something like the closing of the stomata itself, etc.
或者是說像氣孔的關閉本身等等
It also needs to go through some molecular reactions
它也是需要經由一些分子的反應
For example, the permeability of some ions needs to be changed
比如說一些離子的通透要改變
And then some paying hormones are going to be involved
然後一些支付荷爾蒙要參與在裡面
It will help the stomata to close freely
它才會幫助氣孔能夠自由的關閉
The stomata are like a rod-shaped cell
氣孔就像一個身杖型的細胞
One side is thicker and the other is thinner
一邊比較厚一邊比較薄
So when water comes in it will ride away
所以說水進來的時候它就會乘開
It closes when the water goes out
水出去的時候它就會合起來
So decide when the water is going to come in
所以決定什麼時候水要進來
water going out
水要出去
Then this is related to the many ions in the cell
那這個是跟細胞裡面很多離子
plus ion
比如說加離子
Or maybe some payment hormone is related to a control of cleavage into acid
或者是一些支付荷爾蒙相似離成酸的一個控制有關係
So it does have some molecular biology
所以這的確都有一些分子生物
The above academic qualifications can explain
學上面的學歷可以說明
good
好
Classmate Ye from behind
後面的葉同學
Teacher, thank you for your wonderful speech
老師謝謝你精彩的演講
I think what you're describing is
我想一下這些您所介紹的是
More about plants with leaves
關於有葉子的植物比較多
Those receptors that respond to these light
那跟這些反應都光的這些受體
Is it different on top of the extra plants
在多餘的植物上面是不是是不一樣
succulent plants
多肉植物
For example, like a cactus or Lu Hui
比如說像仙人掌或是盧慧
I'm sorry I designed less
對不起我設計得比較少
i don't know if there are some
我不知道有沒有一些
basic research in science
科學上一些基礎的研究
Be Valued Above These Succulents
在這些多肉植物上面被重視
there may be one in
可能有一個是在
Inside some succulent plants by the sea
一些海邊的一些多肉植物裡面
Some studies have been done, such as anti-inflammation
有做一些比如說抗炎的研究
part of the light receptor
那光的受體的部分
let me see
我想想
The light receptors themselves may be relatively few
光的受體本身可能比較少
But some changes in some patterns of light
但是一些光的一些型態變化
or a reaction to adversity
或是逆境的反應
There will be quite a lot
能到時候還蠻多的
good
好
the dark green one
那個有暗綠的
Just now that Dr. Wu talked about light
剛才那個吳博士講到光
White light Blue light Red light
白光 藍光 紅光
I have a very simple
我有一個很簡單的
Compare Snorkeling Questions
比較浮潛的問題
it's inside our house
就是我們家裡面
such as flowers
比如養的花
what if my light bulb
那如果我的燈泡
replace it with the white one
換成那個白的
or change to red
或者換成紅的
change to blue
換成藍的
Does it have this effect on them?
對他們的影響是不是有這個影響
For you, the question is actually very practical.
對 你這問題事實上是非常有實際
I have the same situation myself
我自己也遇到一樣的狀況
It is the plant that I grow in my home
就是我在不管是長家裡的植物
or grow lab plants
或是長實驗室的植物
Every light tube on the body is
身上每個燈管就是
It has its own special spectrum
它都有它自己特殊的光譜
that mostly we see that white
那大部分我們看到那種白色的
spring white kind
春白色的那種
It often has a slightly lower red light
它常常紅光的亮就會稍微低一點點
that some will also depend on how long it's been used
那有些也會根據它使用的時間
There will be a slightly different wavelength of color light
會有一點點不同的波長的色光
will subside a little
會有一點消退
So when I use it in the laboratory
所以說我自己在實驗室裡面使用的時候
I sometimes say
我會有時候如果說
There are some machines that can measure the full spectrum
有一些機器可以測量全光譜
Or buy light bulbs to eat like Philippine fu
或者是燈泡買來吃像菲律賦
it will often
它常常就會
it's actually on the site
它事實上在網站上面
It's been a long time since it's the model of the light bulb
它久違是跟它燈泡的型號的
some spectral values
一些光譜的數值
Then if you find it 600
那如果說你發現它600
Or a band around 400
或者是400左右的波段
when relatively low
比較低的時候
Well, there are actually some light bulbs in the house.
那其實家裡有一些燈泡
Can add some red light
可以補一些紅光
actually helps
事實上會有幫助
The color of the flower and the light
那花的顏色跟那個光
Does the light source matter?
光源有沒有關係
For example, do red flowers need to use red light?
比如說紅色的花是不是就要用紅光
Or blue flowers, purple flowers need to use blue light
或者藍色的花 紫色的花就要用藍光
Is there such a saying?
有這個說法嗎
I would think there should be no
我會覺得應該沒有
Maybe their different colors are in his cells
那可能他們不一樣的顏色是跟他細胞裡面
There are some different color families
有一些不一樣的色屬系
The result of receiving different lengths of light
收不同的破長的光線所造成的結果
So say I think if say
所以說我想如果說
To have a plant that should be, say, healthy
要有一個應該是比如說健康的植物
He may be more colorful
他可能顏色會比較鮮艷
That will allow the plants themselves to grow better
那能夠讓植物本身能夠長得比較好
Maybe his original color will show up just fine
也許他原本的顏色就會呈現得很好
Should not require special light to handle
應該不需要特殊的光線來處理
good
好
wait for me to bring you later
後面先等我帶給你
press the green
按那個綠色的
hello teacher
那個老師你好
i want to ask
我想請問一下
It is in the item grown in our laboratory
就是我們實驗室生長的項裡面
sometimes a light pipe
有時候會有一根燈管
Because it is a fluorescent tube
因為都是一根跟日光燈管
So if one of the light bulbs is broken
那如果說有一根燈管壞掉
that would affect the plants
那對植物影響會有
Will it affect its germination rate or something?
會不會影響到它萌芽率之類的
I think what you're asking is
我想你問到的就是說
If it is said that some places in my growth box are relatively dark
如果說我一個生長箱裡面有的地方比較暗
Some places are brighter, will it make any difference?
有的地方比較亮會不會有什麼差別
If you say you want
那如果說你要
Research is a reaction to light
研究是一個跟光的反應
We have just introduced some very typical light reactions that are related to
我們剛剛介紹到一些很典型的光的反應有相關的
say you want to measure flowering time
說你要測量開花的時間
You want to measure progress, growth, etc.
你要測量進步的生長等等
That
那
My suggestion is that I hope you can try your best to get what you want
我的建議就是說會希望你能夠儘量把你要
Different research groups and control groups in the experiment
做實驗的各個不同的研究組跟對照組
Can be placed under relatively consistent light brightness
能夠放在比較一致的光的亮度下面
to experiment
來做實驗
so as not to have some appearance that you will see
那免得有一些你會看到的一些外表型
Could be because it's not getting enough light or too much light
可能是因為它的光線不足或是光線太多所造成的
So maybe add more lights
所以也許加更燈管吧
just can't pull it out
就是拔不過去
That's because the teacher I am
那因為老師我是
Because I put them all on the same plate
因為我都放在同一個盤子裡面
so i guess they should be ok
所以我想它們應該是還好
Just saying sometimes I find mine
只是說有的時候我會發現我的
certain multium it may
某一些multium它可能
Germination rate becomes worse
萌芽率就變差了
then i don't know
那我不曉得
does this have anything to do with it
跟這個有沒有關係
Yes, in fact, the germination of many plants is regulated by light.
會 事實上植物很多植物的萌芽都很受到光線的調控
So if you have observed it this thing
所以說如果你有觀察它這件事情
like in fact nice
像事實上很好
Maybe its a new one in the process of transmitting light information
搞不好是一個新的在光的訊息傳導的過程裡面
involved in it
有參與在裡面
Then you just said put them on the same plate
那你剛講說放在同一個盤子裡面
This is of course already good
這當然是已經很好的
Already in line with a situation where the environment can be unified
已經很符合環境能夠統一的一個狀況
It's actually quite simple
那事實上有很簡單
Some light photometers can measure light
有些光的 光度計是可以測量光線的
So you can be in the middle of the four corners
所以你可以在四個角中間
Grab a few points left and right to measure a little
左右抓幾個點稍微測量一下
if the light
如果說光線
I suggest maybe not too much difference
我是建議可能不要差太多
that is close to
就是說接近
Or you can rotate a little bit
或者是說你能夠稍微旋轉一下
Allow the plant to be evenly illuminated by the light
讓這個植物能夠均勻的受到光線的照射
maybe ideal
也許比較理想
Thank you, teacher
謝謝老師
Talk a little bit tonight
今天晚上說一兩多
I want to use the leek as a metaphor
我想拿一個那個韭菜以韭黃來做一個比喻
Is it the same growth period
它的生長期是不是一樣
Is there any difference in its nutritional value?
還有它的營養價值有沒有差別
Sorry I may not be able to answer this question
抱歉這個問題我可能沒有辦法回答
hit you
給打你
Leek and Leek King are
韭菜跟韭王就是
Maybe one belongs to the white seedlings that have not been illuminated
可能一個是屬於沒有照光的白苗
Then one is an illuminated green tissue
然後一個是有照光的綠色的組織
I'm really sorry about the nutritional value part
那營養價值的部分真的很抱歉
Maybe it has something to do with liking
也許跟喜好也有
Everyone has different preferences
每個人喜好不同也有差異
Thanks
謝謝
ok, the one behind
好 後面那位
Hello, Mr. Wu
阿吳老師你好
I want to ask you about the video I just saw
想請教一下剛才看到那個影片
His chloroplast goes towards the light
他那個業率體會向著光過去
how did he move there
那他是怎麼移動過去的
Thanks
謝謝
good
好
Today just happened to be because of time I didn't have a chance
今天剛好有因為時間的關係我沒有機會
Ah Xiu can show you
可以阿修給你們看
In fact, inside the cell
事實上細胞裡面
We will feel that the cells in the whole cell
我們會覺得整個細胞裡面的細胞
just like a swimming pool
只好像是一個游泳池一樣
then very empty
然後很空曠
But in fact the inside of the cell is like when I was a child
但是事實上細胞裡面是像我小時候的
as fast as the swimming pool
游泳池一樣很急
Just because there were not so many facilities back then
就是因為那時候沒有那麼多的設施
So there are many people soaking in the swimming pool
所以就是游泳池裡面都泡了很多人
There is a special structure inside the cell
那在細胞裡面有一個特殊的構造
cytoskeleton
叫做細胞骨骼
Cytoskeleton
細胞骨骼
In fact, it was found that the movement of cells in the chloroplast is pulled by these cytoskeletons
事實上是發現細胞在葉綠體裡面移動是由這些細胞骨骼來牽引
It is acting micro filament
就是 acting micro filament
it will pull it will wrap on the chloroplast
它會牽引它會包裹在葉綠體上面
Then there is a directional movement by means of aggregation, polymerization and depolarization
然後利用聚合跟 polymerization跟 depolarization的方式有一個方向性的移動
So if you can calibrate the position of these cytoskeletons
所以說你如果能夠標定這些細胞骨骼的位置的話
you'll find it afterglow outside and pull it over
你就會發現它殘照在外面然後把它拉過去
so
所以
Sorry, the one just said that the cellular chloroplasts hide behind other chloroplasts
對不起 那個剛才說細胞葉綠體會躲在其他葉綠體後面
That's who pushed the first one out
那是誰把第一個推出去了
Are you saying who is willing to sacrifice themselves or who
你說是誰願意犧牲自己嗎還是說是誰
who decides the first
是誰決定第一個
This might be more like fate
這個可能比較是命運
But its original place is there
可是它原來的位置在那裡
and then sometimes
然後有時候是
because it might want to go back
因為它也許很想去後面
But the space is no longer allowed
可是空間已經不容許了
But it can be
不過這倒是可以就是
If there is a way to track a single chloroplast, I can see if there is a braver one
如果有辦法追蹤單顆葉綠體的話倒是可以看看是不是有比較勇敢
Chloroplasts recommended for Yonghui
建議勇回的葉綠體
Mr. Wu, from the perspective of bionics, if the artificial plants are present, can he do the same thing as the real plants, that is, the effect of light ears?
吳老師,有仿生學的角度,目前人造植物的話,他可以做到跟真的植物一樣,就是進行光耳作用嗎?
Okay, thank you
好,謝謝
This is actually the goal that many people want to achieve, that is to say, I dont want to talk about plants first, it may be more complicated
這個其實是很多人想要達成的目標,就是說,我想先不要講植物,可能是要比較複雜一點
That may mean from the smallest point, how can I create a new, that is, an artificial cell, and then be able to perform the function of a cell
那可能從最小就是說,我要怎麼樣才能夠造成一個新的,就是一個人造的細胞,然後能夠執行一個細胞的功能
Only by getting there first can we get to a plant, that is to say, like in a plant, maybe the roadside weed we just saw is very innocent, but there are tens of thousands of genes in the genome
那先到那裡,才有辦法到一個植物,就是說,像在植物裡面,也許我們剛剛看到這個路邊野草非常不欺言,可是在基因組裡面有好幾萬個基因
There are thousands of single white matter in the karma body, which need to work together to construct
那業力體裡面有好幾千個單白質,需要共同的作用來構造
So, if what you said just now means, from things to beings, it means how I build it, using the knowledge I already know in genetics
所以說,如果您剛剛講的就是說,從物到有的意思嘛,就是說我怎麼樣建造,利用我現在在基因學已經知道的知識
How to build a complete cell, or a complete plant individual
怎麼樣構築一個完整的細胞,或是一個完整的植物的個體
of course
那這當然
Everyone is very interested, maybe in reproductive energy, and also hope to use the karma body as a generator, specially to manufacture the things we need
大家很感興趣,也許在生殖能,也希望能夠把業率體當作一個發電機,專門來製造我們需要的東西
I think there is still room for effort, because we don't fully understand the number of genes involved and its structure
我想還有一段努力的空間,因為它所參與的基因的數目還有它的結構,我們目前並沒有充分了解
Therefore, there is no way to independently let the karma body survive in the cells alone, without combined genes
所以還沒有辦法獨立的讓業率體獨自在細胞裡面生存,沒有合的基因
Because now most of the proteins, most of the genes in most karma bodies, the genes that make these proteins, most of them have been sent to the cells to go through the process of internal engineering, and they have all entered the nucleus of the cells.
因為現在大部分業率體所裡面所有的蛋白質大部分的基因,製造這些蛋白質的基因,大部分都已經送到細胞經過內工生的過程,都已經進到細胞核裡面
So it needs the existence of the nucleus, so that the karmic body can function normally
所以它需要細胞核的存在,業率體才有辦法正常的運作
So there may be a way to go, but it is also a direction that many people are interested in
所以可能有一段路要走,但是也是一個很多人感興趣的方向
child
小本人
Mr. Wen, thank you very much for suddenly entering my file
溫老師,非常謝謝你突然進入我的文件
Thanks
謝謝
Because what you are talking about today is all about conception, it seems that from listening to your documents, it seems that conception decides to punch
因為你今天講的都是觀,好像從聽你的文件來講,好像觀決定一拳
Then I just said, does the temperature also matter?
那我只是說,那溫度是不是也有觀?
You said this flower, whether it will bloom or not
你說這個花 指令開不開花
Is that temperature also brings you a little bit of character Thank you
那是不是溫度也帶給你一點角色 謝謝
Of course it is
當然 就是
Especially today, here I just saw a teacher Chang
尤其是今天 在這我剛剛看有一個常老師
He is in our agricultural and biological center, he specializes in temperature
他就是在我們農生中心 他是專門做溫度
Wait a minute when I have no way to answer, I will
等一下我那個沒有辦法回答的時候我就
ask him to help me
請他幫我
It's the debit number
就是 扣號
That's right. I can have a discount number.
就是 對 扣號 我可以有一個扣號號
That temperature is indeed
那 溫度的確是的
For example, you still remember
就是比如說 大家還記得
I just developed that beautiful purple flower in my academic qualifications
剛剛在學歷裡面開發那種很漂亮的紫色小花
It's actually inside and outside the petals
它實際上就是在花瓣裡面內外
Feel the difference in temperature
感受溫度的不一樣
That is, when the inside feels the temperature, it will grow faster
就是內部感受溫度的時候會長得比較快
So from the petals will open
所以從花瓣會打開
So the temperature in the environment is
所以說 溫度在環境裡面是
A very important factor in controlling plant growth
控制植物生長一個非常重要的因素
The temperature is high and low
那溫度高跟低
High temperature is harmful to plants
溫度高對植物來講是一種傷害
Low temperature is also a kind of damage to plants
溫度低對植物來講也是一種傷害
So there is a relationship between personnel and temperature
所以人事和溫度有一個認居
Just to make us feel more comfortable
就是讓我們人覺得比較舒適
The same is true for plants
對植物來講也是一樣
So in the environment
所以說 環境裡面
I'm sorry I just had another
很抱歉 我剛剛又 我
Excessively fond of loving my own research work
過度喜歡熱愛我自己的研究工作
So I'm going to emphasize it as the only important factor in the world
所以我就把它強調成世界上唯一的重要的因素
but you are exactly right
但是您講的exactly對
That is, no matter the temperature in the environment
就是環境裡面不管是溫度
In fact, temperature and light often interact with each other.
然後其實溫度跟光線有很多時候會互相的
because when the light shines
因為說照光的時候
The pig's body temperature rises
豬的體溫就變高了
So the eyes sometimes come together
所以雙眼有時候會連帶著來
that temperature can also
那溫度也可以
high daytime temperature
白天的溫度高
low temperature at night
晚上的溫度低
Sometimes you don't need to deal with light
有時候你不需要有光線的處理
Just one high temperature and one low temperature
只要一個高溫一個低溫
can also make living organisms always establish
也能夠造就生物始終的建立
So the temperature is really good for pigs
所以溫度的確對豬來講
is also a very important environmental factor
也是一個非常重要的環境的因子
your classmate
您這邊同學
next is
下一個是
Teacher, I want to ask
老師我想詢問一下就是
Those photoblast proteins
那這些光壽體蛋白質
it if
它如果
because we now need to know
因為我們現在要知道
The climate is changing now
現在氣候一直在變遷
It is possible that the intensity of the light
那有可能那個光照的強度
will always change
也會一直在改變
Then will it affect the mechanisms of these light-should bodies?
那它會不會影響到這些光壽體的這些機質
its proportional
它的比例上
change with long-term changes
就隨著長期的變化就改變了
This is the first question
這是第一個問題
Then the second question is
然後第二個問題是
just want to ask
想詢問一下就是
like a spitting lion
類似像吐獅子那種
This plant that can parasitize on others
能寄生在別人身上的這種植物
Does he have this skinny protein?
他身上有沒有這種光瘦體的蛋白質
The second question you mentioned is also what I really want to know.
你講的第二個問題也是我很想要知道的
That is to say broadly speaking
就是說廣份來講
That is to say, these parasitic plants
就是說這些寄生植物
How much of it is from others and how much is produced by himself
他到底有多少是用人家的多少是自己產生的
Then I haven't dabbled in it myself.
那我自己是沒有涉獵到
Just have you ever studied the synopsis itself?
就是有沒有研究過突視子本身
Is his skinny body his own or someone else's?
他的光瘦體是自己的還是別人的
Natus itself actually has a very incomplete karma body
那突視子本身其實有非常不完整的業率體
So he actually
所以說他其實
He doesn't have a lot of light-type development himself.
他本身也沒有很多光型態的發育
So I'm thinking maybe he has some similar genes
所以我在想也許他也有一些類似的基因
But I don't know if it still works
但不知道是不是還是有功能的
but this should take a look
但是這應該要看一下
I haven't read any reports about it
我是沒有讀到相關的報導
Then your other question is
那你的另外一個問題就是
In the change of light environment
在光環境的改變當中
Is it true that these light thin bodies of plants will also make some adjustments
是不是植物這些光瘦體也會做一些調整
to respond to changes in the environment
來因應環境的變遷
Then I think the research on thin body in nature now
那我想現在在自然界裡面光瘦體的研究
has given us some temperament
已經給我們一些氣質
just some ideas
就是一些想法
so it's possible
所以這是有可能的
Its stability is relatively low when it is illuminated
它在照光的時候它的穩定度比較低
For example, luciferin A
比如說光明素A
its stability when it is illuminated
它在照光的時候它的穩定度
It can't move its fingers and is very intolerant to light
它就動不在指就是很不耐照光
because if it is exposed to light it will be taken to magnetic therapy
因為照光它就會被帶去磁療
So maybe it's also possible to use this way to
所以說也許也可以利用這樣子的方式來
In response to the high light intensity in the environment
因應環境裡面說光強度高的時候
It is the amount of luciferin A that will exist
它就是光明素A的量就會存在
the amount will be less
量就會比較少
this is also a way
這樣也是一個方式
It not only accepts light
它不僅接受光線
also let the light control its own amount inside the cell
也讓光線控制它自己在細胞裡面的量
After controlling the amount it is able to receive the
控制的量之後它能夠接收的
naturally less
自然也就比較少
So take advantage of these mutual feedback
所以利用這些互相回饋的這些
The control mechanism can also allow
調控機制也可以讓
The composition of the plant body that changes its own photoripe body
植物體裡面改變它自己光熟體的成分
composition and weight
組成跟重量
So there is an opportunity to reach
所以有機會可以達到
Communicate more closely with the environment
跟環境溝通的更密切
or more delicate
或是更delicate
ok one last question please sir
好最後一個問題請那位先生
teacher ask
老師請教一下
Short Manufacturing Plant vs. Long Manufacturing Plant
短製造植物跟長製造植物
Usually a diurnal flowering plant
一般是只白天開花的植物
Plants that bloom at night
請問夜間開花的植物
Is it also possible to stipulate
是不是也可以這樣規定
conversation
談話
talk to
談話 對
I really do not know
我真的不知道
but I
但我
Teacher Qiu is closer to me
邱老師離我比較近
so i can look it up and tell her
所以我可以查完答案之後再告訴她
So if there are other questions today I don't know
所以說今天如果還有其他問題是我不曉得的
That is to say, you should be able to find Huiyinmiao on the Internet.
就是說網路上應該可以找回音廟
Also tell me the problem
也順便告訴我問題
Then I have a chance to learn new answers
然後我就有機會學回新的答案
Teacher Qiu, I will tell you when I find it
邱老師我找到之後告訴你
OK I think so
OK 我想是
about the time
有差不多時間的關係
really tired
也實在很累
today i think
今天我想
There is a classmate who can continue
有一個同學可以繼續
influential
有影響
Ask privately
私下請教
we'll call it a day
我們今天就到此為止
Thank you all for coming to the stormy night
也謝謝大家的風雨之夜來捧場
hope everyone
希望大家
min GPA o Canada min GPA o Toronto
MING PAO CANADA MING PAO TORONTO
you
you